<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three great questions concerning the succession and the dangers of popery fully examin'd in a letter to a Member of this present Parliament.</title>
            <author>M. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R50</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229912</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2357:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three great questions concerning the succession and the dangers of popery fully examin'd in a letter to a Member of this present Parliament.</title>
                  <author>M. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>re-printed in the year, 1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to M.R. by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153272:1"/>
            <p>THREE Great Queſtions Concerning the SUCCESSION AND THE Dangers
of Popery, FULLY EXAMIND, IN A LETTER TO A MEMBER of this Preſent
PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-Printed in the Year, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153272:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153272:2"/>
            <head>Three great Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ESTIONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere never did, nor perhaps ever will come, a matter of greater
importance, taking in all circumſtances, before a Parliament, than the of
late much agitated buſineſs of Succeſſion; upon the right ſtating
whereof, the preſent and future quiet and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of this poor
diſtracted Nation, does inevitably depend. I cannot therefore, Sir, but
extremely commend your reſolution, and wiſh the ſame to all your Fellow
Members, of conſidering fully ſo momentous an Affair; wherein, that I may
give you all posſible ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will in their order lay before you
my naked ſenſe upon every of your queſtions, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Whether the
Parliament have power to alter the Succeſſion? 2. Allowing that they have,
whether the reaſons on which the late Houſe of Commons proceeded againſt
the <hi>D.</hi> to wit, his departure from the Church of <hi>England</hi> to
that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thereby giving Birth and Life to the late damnable
and Helliſh Plot, be ſufficient? 3. What dangers the Nation will be under,
in caſe the Crown deſcends upon a Popiſh Succeſſor, or more
particularly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>R. H.</hi> Theſe Queſtions are great and
Weighty, and their ſolution requires not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greater prudence and
judgement, but great courage and honeſty; I wiſh I could be equally
confident, I ſhould not be found wanting in the former, as I am certain I
ſhal not in the latter. But that I may no longer keep you from pasſing your
own cenſure in both inſtances, I deſire, you will conſider
ſeriouſly, not only the frame and conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Laws, but likewiſe thoſe of Nature; for on the due conſideration of both,
the true An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to your Queſtions muſt be founded.</p>
            <p>Man was no ſooner brought into the World, than he found he could
not preſerve his beeing, nor attain the end ont's happineſs, without
entring into ſociety; nor yet, having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into ſociety, without a
ſtrict obſervance of compacts and agreements; that all men, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a
natural equal right to all things, there could be no Society without Government
and order: That to ſecure this State, it was neceſſary, Men ſhould not
only keep their Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſpeak truth with their Neighbours, but
ſubmit themſelves to a Governour, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently impowered in all
diſputes, to force their complyance to his final ſentence and
determination; it was requiſite to put into his hand, an unlimited abſolute
Power, becauſe otherwiſe it could not be ſupreme, nor he their Governour:
For the exerciſe of this they choſe the moſt wiſe, honeſt, and
couragious Perſon, binding him to no other Law, than what in reaſon and
conſcience he ſhould find moſt conducing to the <hi>good</hi> of the
<hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity,</hi> founded upon that Golden and Eternal Law of Reaſon, of
Nature, <hi>of doing to all Men as you would be done unto.</hi> For pasſion
and ſelf-intereſt diſabling Men from judging aright in their own caſes,
they wiſely made a man without private intereſt, themſelves agreeing to
ſupport his expences, and thereby placing him above controverſies of his
own, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an impartial common Father, not posſible to be more kind or
indulgent to one than to another, while they continued equally obedient. Now,
becauſe their attendance upon la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour would incapacitate themſelves, and
that one could not have a better pretence than<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153272:3"/>another, they
alſo agreed, that the Empire ſhould be hereditary; conſidering that not
only inſtruction which none elſe could give, but likewiſe the vertues of
the Father might with the bloud be tranſmitted to the Children; 
<q> 
                  <l>— Sed diu</l> 
                  <l>Lateque victrices catervae</l> 
                  <l>Conſiliis juvenis revictae,</l> 
                  <l>Senſere quid mens rite, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d indoles</l> 
                  <l>Nutrit afauſtis ſub penetralibus</l> 
                  <l>Poſset, quid Auguſti paternus</l> 
                  <l>In pueros animus Nerones.</l> 
                  <l>Fortes creantur ſortibus, &amp; bonis</l> 
                  <l>Est in juvencis, eſt in equis patrum</l> 
                  <l>Virtus: nec imbellem feroces</l> 
                  <l>Progenerant aquilae columbam.</l> 
                  <l>Doctrina ſed vim promovet inſitam</l> 
                  <l>Rectique cultus pector aroborant.</l>
                  <bibl>Hor. l. 4. Car.
Ode. 4.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <q> 
                  <l>But even they, who ſpread their Arms ſo far,</l> 
                  <l>Arms uſed as much to Victory as war,</l> 
                  <l>By the brave Youth o'recome, were taught to know,</l> 
                  <l>What a great mind, as greatly bred cou'd do,</l> 
                  <l>What mighty things by him must needs be wrought,</l> 
                  <l>Whom <hi>Nero</hi> got, and whom <hi>Auguſtus</hi>
taught.</l> 
                  <l>Courage and vertue in the blood are ſown,</l> 
                  <l>Nature in this her ſelf has equal ſhown:</l> 
                  <l>The brave are Sparks but of their Fathers Fire.</l> 
                  <l>In Beaſts weſee the vertue of the Sire;</l> 
                  <l>Nor does the Kingly Bird, belov'd of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>Stain his great Race and hatch a feeble Dove.</l> 
                  <l>Education urges on to deeds,</l> 
                  <l>The inbred vertue ſleeping in it's ſeeds,</l> 
                  <l>With nobler thoughts inſpires Heroick minds,</l> 
                  <l>And ſtrengthens all the greatneſs that it finds.</l>
               </q>a
Rule that can no more faile in Men, than in Beaſts, but when interrupted by
ſome very accountable accidents.</p>
            <p>Wiſdom having thus brought men from the ſtate of War and
Poverty, into a condition, of peace and plenty, tis plain nothing but folly and
madneſs can diſturb or deſtroy that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. 'Tis then very evident,
that whether you conſider Mankind, like muſhrooms, ſprung up in the
night, as the Poets Fable of the <hi>Dragons</hi> Teeth ſlain by
<hi>Cadmus</hi> and ſown in the ground, the Foundation of <hi>Hobs</hi>'s
fancy, as before him of <hi>Ariſtotles;</hi> or deduce as more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant
to reaſon, and Scripture, his origine from one Man; the grounds of Government
and Obedience muſt ſtill have been the ſame, and founded upon the
foregoing conſiderations; whence it will evidently appear, that in all parts
of the World, Empire muſt have been Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical at the beginning. To this
truth not only profane, but ſacred ſtory bears Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. <hi>Principio
rerum,</hi> ſayes an Author of great credit, <hi>gentium nationumque imperium
penes Reges erat:</hi> And wherever in the old Teſtament Government is
ſpoken of, whether of the <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Adam</hi> downwards, or of
the Neighbour Nations, even of ſuch little ones, as were confined within
Walls, as of <hi>Jericho, Tyre, and Sidon,</hi> there is no mention but of
Kings, and ſingle Rulers, till after the death of <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<hi>Joſhua;</hi> when the Tribes divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their common bond, began to
ſet up Chiefs and Heads of their own degenerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by degrees from Monarchys,
their primitive inſtitution; but meeting with ill ſucceſs in all their
changes, they begg'd at laſt to have, <hi>like other Nations a King to go in
and out before them.</hi> This having been, and ſtill being the moſt
general, we may ſafely conclude it, the<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153272:3"/>beſt of all
conſtitutions; But as there is nothing certain, not fix'd in the Univerſe,
but al things in perpetual fluctuation, ſo the manner of Dominion has met
with many changes and revolutions in the ſeveral Ages and parts of the World,
according to the prudence or imprudence of Governours, and other concurring
accidents. From one where the power was firſt veſted, it fell into the
Hands of a few, and from the few into the hands of many, where finding no
reſting place, but ſoon falling into Anarchy and confuſion, it wheel'd
about again to it's firſt form; and yet even there, the unſteady courſe
of humane affairs permits it no longer to continue, then till the unequal
courage and vertues of the Succeſſors, make way for the incroachments of
the Ambitious, or the folly and madneſs of the giddy mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to give it
freſh rounds and turns: So that if a man would examine things ſtrictly, he
would find more reaſon to give to every of the Governments of the World,
rather the name of a fluctuating Oligarchy, than that by which they are
commonly called; for upon exact ſcrutiny it would perhaps be found, that even
the moſt abſolute Monarchs admit ſome He or She Privadoes, or Copartners
into the managment of their Scepters. In the beginning the burden of a Crown
was not ſo heavy, nor the cares ſo many, as to need Adviſers, or
Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; then Integrity was ſo great in Prince and People, that his will,
was their undiſputed law, the emergent Dictates of his pleaſure, no written
conſtitutions, ſilenc'd all their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies: <hi>Populus nullis
legibus tenebatur arbitria Principum pro legibus erant.</hi> But after upon
great increaſe, and ſpreading of mankind, the Princes found it
neceſſary (as <hi>Jethro, Moſes</hi> Father in law, had done in the
caſe of the <hi>Jews</hi>) to diſtribute ſome part of their power, but
with dependence upon themſelves, among the Elders, chief and wiſeſt of
their people, and to conſult with them, at their pleaſure, in all the
weighty Affairs of ſtate. Hence came the <hi>Egyptians Magi,</hi> not
Conjurers as is commonly received, but Aſtronomers and Counſellors of
State, the beſt Judges of <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> in a Country,
where thoſe boundaries were often interrupted, by the overflowings of
<hi>Nilus;</hi> to this likewiſe are owing the Eaſtern Monarchs,
<hi>Sophies,</hi> Colledges of wiſe and diſintereſſed Philoſophers,
and ſtudying and employ'd in the good of their Countreys, as well thoſe of
<hi>China. Indoſtan,</hi> or the great <hi>Mogul;</hi> the <hi>Tartars,</hi>
and the <hi>Perſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> as of
others; After whoſe Exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s the
<hi>Turks</hi> inſtituted their <hi>Divans,</hi> practiced by the Emperours
of <hi>Fez</hi> and <hi>Morocco,</hi> and by all the reſt of <hi>Africa.</hi>
The ſame reaſons gave the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Prieſts, and the
<hi>Druids</hi> (of the Gauls and <hi>Brittians,</hi> originally the ſame
peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) their power, and to the <hi>Jews</hi> their Sanhedrim; to the
<hi>Germans</hi> their Dyets, and to the <hi>Romans</hi> their Senate, to the
<hi>Pope</hi> as a temporal Prince, his Colledge of Cardinals; to the
<hi>Saxons,</hi> our immediate Anceſtors, not to inſtance in more, their
<hi>Wittena Gemot,</hi> or great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, ſince the <hi>Norman</hi>
conqueſt alter'd in Name and other circumſtances; though not in the
foundation, to that of our preſent Parliaments. In all which 'tis very
obſervable, that the Prieſts the Flamens, and Archflamens, (for ſuch
there were among the moſt barbarous, who had their glimmerings of a future
life) always held the firſt form, and were in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment even of State
Affairs, of greateſt credit. But to paſs by the reſt, and come to our
own, in which we are moſt immediatly concern'd, we ſhall find, that upon
the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires going to wrack, and their Colonies with many of the
Natives being hence drained, to ſupport it's tottering State; there aroſe a
contention between the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tiains</hi> and the Picts, for the dominion of this Iſland; they
were both originally the ſame people, but the <hi>Picts</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the
vaſſalage and the Cuſtoms of the <hi>Romans,</hi> to which the other had
ſubmitted, fled into the extremeſt parts called <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> Inhabitants, who were anciently known by no other Name, and
now returning with aſſiſtance, were too hard for the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</hi>
Hereupon they were forced to intreat the help of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> a Warlike
people of <hi>Germany.</hi> The motion being communicated by
<hi>Hengiſt,</hi> to whom it was firſt made, they embraced it,
conditionally they might have the continuance of their own Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom
and the conquer'd Country equall ydivided, among the Adventurers; for they
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took not the voyage, ſo much with deſign of aſſiſtance to
others, as of advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Hengiſt</hi> ſurmiſing this
to the Leaders, they ſoon aſſembled and drew together 9000 men, beſides
Wowen and Children. On the confines of the River <hi>Elbe,</hi> as their
Neighbours the <hi>Franks</hi> had done before, on the Banks of <hi>Sala;</hi>
and as theſe did here ſo did they thre enact by mutual agreement, the
performance of thoſe Artcles, appointing that <hi>Hengiſt</hi> and his 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153272:4"/>line ſhould be their Leaders, and their Kings; reſerving
to themſelves, the power of choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a new Monarch, only upon the failure
of his iſſue. Accordingly they ſet ſail, and ſoon arriving in
<hi>England,</hi> had firſt the Iſle of <hi>Thanet,</hi> and after
<hi>Kent</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſigned for their
Province; after many bickerings, freſh ſupplies, and inundations of their
own People, they at laſt not only drive out the <hi>Picts</hi> and
<hi>Scots,</hi> but even the <hi>Brittains;</hi> forcing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem into the remote part of
<hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Cornwall;</hi> the certain conſequence of unnatural
civil Wars, and diſſentions; where the contending Parties ever become
looſers, making way for ſome ſtranger, or third Perſon to ſnatch a
way the prize. Policy would have taught the <hi>Brittains,</hi> that Leagues
with an overpowerful State always prove deſtructive to the weaker; and that
they could not reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably have expected, from forreign asſiſtance, any
other fate than that of the Lamb in the fable, who calling for the Lyons aid
againſt the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, had only the
pleaſure of ſeeing him firſt chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, and himſelf immediately
after devoured; or then that of the Mouſe and the Frog, who while ſtriving
with each other for the maſtery, gave the Kite an opportunity of ſweeping
away both. Not to inſtance more remotely, it was this that ſoon after upon
the <hi>Saxon</hi> diviſions, encouraged the invaſion of the
<hi>Danes,</hi> and gave <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>Normans,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And not long ſince while King and
Parliament were diſputing for the Supremacy, Liberty and Prerogative, made
the way for others to deſtroy both, and inſtead of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent well
temper'd Government, to ſet up an intolerable, and moſt arbitary Tyranny. I
hope the ſenſe of the unexpresſible calamities, under which the Nation
then groan'd, will teach us to avoid ſuch miſeries for the future; another
civil War, being like without a miracle, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave us to a Tyrant of
another Nation, which like the Devils entring in a ſecond time, wou'd make
our latter condition, ſeven fold worſe than the former; from which in all
appearance, nothing but Providence, and a Spirit of moderation, and concord,
can defend our Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Saxons</hi> having at length gain'd the Victory, purſued
their reſolutions, even during the Heptarchy, as far as the frequent and
almoſt continued Wars would permit: after the ſtronger had ſwallowed up
the reſt, they centured into a ſingle Monarchie; and in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of
<hi>Alfred,</hi> Collected into one body the ſubſtance of their Laws,
attempted before in part by K. <hi>Ina:</hi> and yet to be met with in
<hi>Lambert.</hi> The execution of theſe by the after incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the
<hi>Danes,</hi> being interrupted, they were at laſt methodiz'd by the
Confeſſor; by whoſe death, the <hi>Normans</hi> poſſeſſed the
Crown, they were rejected, &amp; the uſages of their own Countrey, and the
effects of their Princes will, in their ſtead, impoſed upon the people; who
Stomaching their being thus enſlaved, after long grumblings, and often
calling to be ruled by the Laws of holy <hi>Edward,</hi> they had by firs the
reſtoration of them in great meaſure, eſpecially in the firſt
<hi>Harry's</hi> days, the better to ſecure his Uſurpation. But that not
continuing, at length a Rebellion broke forth, &amp; produced the confirmation
of them, in the great <hi>Charter,</hi> or <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> which in the
main, as the beſt Lawyers will tel you, is nothing elſe but the repetition,
or examplification of their old Ordinances, and ever ſince have been the
foundation of all our Statutes. According to theſe the people were to be
Governed, Liberty and Property ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the incroachments of
invaders, and Juſtice to be diſtributed in the ſeveral Shares, or Shires
of <hi>England,</hi> as in <hi>Germany,</hi> where <hi>Tacitus</hi> tells us,
<hi>Jura per pagos reddebant;</hi> For to make their conditions moſt eaſie,
the controverſies were to be determined in their own Voiſinage, by the
Hundreder, or Lord of the Mannor, from whom they might appeal to the
<hi>Comes,</hi> or Lord of the Countie, who, with the aſſiſtance of
ſeveral Aldermanni, or Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, pronounced ſentence. Upon this Cuſtom
is founded our Judges of Aſſizes, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Juſtices of the
Peace their Aſſeſſors. From this Countie Court, the laſt final Appeal
was to the Great Council, after the Conqueſt called by the name of
Parliament, and compoſed of the great Lords, Spiritual, and Temporal,
aſſembled in the preſence of the King, when, and where he was pleaſed
to ſummon them. To this general meeting, came from all the parts of the
Kingdom, as manie as were aggrieved, either by themſelves, or their
Attorneys, or Lawyers: And hence it is, that we ſo often find it mentioned,
not only in <hi>Spelman,</hi> but in <hi>Hoveden, Malmsbury, Marthew
Paris,</hi> and the reſt of the Monkiſh Writers, that to this <hi>Curia
Magna</hi> did reſort the Princes, Lords, and Chief men, and <hi>Cauſidici
ab omni parte Regni:</hi> From whence aroſe the miſtake in after Ages, as
if thoſe Lawyers, who were only the Attournies,<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153272:4"/>and Pleaders
of their Clients Cauſes, made any part of the great Council, unto which the
Commons, (whatſoever Mr. <hi>Bacon, Petit,</hi> or any former Writers can
ſay of their Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) were not admitted till the latter end of
<hi>Henrie</hi> 3. raign, when he obſerving the difficulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es under which his
Father had long ſtruggled, wiſely allow'd them ſuch a conſtitution, and
particular Priviledges of their own, as might ſerve to Counterballance the
Power of the Lords, grown ſo exorbitant that without due poiſing and equal
Liberation, no otherwiſe to be done, It muſt of neceſſity endanger the
overthrow of the Monarchie, and the diſturbance of the whole Nation. He is
therefore to be accounted the firſt Author of our preſent Parliamentary
uſages, and after his preſcript they to this day receive their Summons, and
their beeing; and yet if we narrowly look into the matter, we ſhall finde
they are more altered in Faſhion than in ſubſtance, notwithſtanding
their often gaining both upon the Crown and the Lords, by the Kings firſt
allowance of their management of the purſe-ſtring of the Kingdom; for the
Lords Houſe alone was made, and ſtill continues the Court of Judicature,
&amp; the ultimate deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Appeals, where according to their firſt
inſtitution, no original Cauſe was to take place; to the houſe of Commons
he has left the firſt motions of Grants, &amp; Aids or Subſidies, who
repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the People now, as the Lawyers did before, and cannot in Propriety
of ſpeech as well as of Juſtice be called by other name, nor allowed
greater Power, than of Attorneys. The write ſayes plainly, The Lords are to
adviſe and deliberate with the King, upon certain weighty affairs of ſtate,
the Commons to conſent, &amp; do what, in ſuch caſes, the King ſhal
thereupon enact; whence it clearly follows, that their Power depends wholly
upon the Princes pleaſure, and reaches <hi>ex inſtituto,</hi> no further
than to the matters by him propounded, and therefore could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle
with any thing elſe without his Permiſſion; The Commons then were called
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to repreſent the peoples grievances, to pray, and receive
redreſs, as the King, with the advice of the Lords ſhould ordain, and to
ſignifie ſo much to the ſeveral places, for which they ſerve; Printing
not being then found out, and promulgation being of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie
to the obligation of all poſitive conſtitution. To this Council the people
flock'd, as their buſineſs, or their humour led them, in confus'd
multitudes repreſenting by petition their grievances; the Lords appointing a
Select number of their own, firſt to conſider whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were fit to be
propounded to the reſt; the ground of our preſent Committees. The Commons
attending bare-headed for the Reſolutions, conſented to them as do
Plaintiffs, and Defendants to the Judges deciſions in the Courts of
<hi>Weſtminster-Hall. Hen.</hi> 3. as was ſaid before, to leſſen the
power of the Lords, and bring a confuſed Aſſembly to a Regular meeting,
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained everie Shire, City, and Burrough to ſend two Knights, and two
Burgeſſes, as Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys for the others: yet till ſometime after, they
had no conſtant Speaker, nor thoſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, of which length of time,
and conceſſions of Kings have given them poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But as neither, nor both Houſes, have any original Right or
Power, but, as all Creatures do upon the Almighty, ſo their Lives depend upon
the Breath of the Princes Noſtrils, and with his Call or Command, come into,
or go out of the World: ſo has the King, on the other ſide, condeſcended
and promiſed, That he will not without their Conſents and Approbations
repeal old, nor make any new Statutes; but more particularly, in thirty three
Parliaments he has confirmed the Foundation of all, <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the
boundaries of their Libertie, and his Prerogative; and in three declar'd it
ſo much unalterable, that any Act of Parliament or Judgement, made or given
contrary to it, ſhall be, and is hereby made <hi>ipſo facto</hi> null and
void. And that with good reaſon; for this being the Summary of all ancient
Laws and Cuſtoms, and the exact Rule and Meaſure of Right and Wrong, as
well between the King and his Subjects, as between one another, made or
confirmed anew by the unanimous conſent of every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Perſon of full
years, at the firſt coming into the Kingdom, and ſubmitting to the
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Hengiſt</hi> and his Succeſſors, and conformable to
the Laws of Nature, of Nations; <hi>Quod tibi non vis fieri alteri non
feceris,</hi> ought without diſpute to remain ſacred and inviolable, and to
be imprinted in the minds of all free-born Subjects, and carried about with
them in their underſtandings, as the Phylacteries of old in the Garments of
the <hi>Jews.</hi> By all which 'tis plain, that as the Kings Image and
Inſcription makes the Coin, ſo his Approbation or <hi>Fiat</hi> makes the
Laws current; and conſequently, the ſupreme Legiſlative Power is ſolely
veſted<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153272:5"/>in him, who may therefore allow or reject at
pleaſure whatever Ordinances his Houſes judge adviſable: The contrary
would be a Soleciſm in Government, giving to the King the Title only, and
leaving to his Subjects the Power of Kingſhip; This making the Governed the
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and therefore implying in it ſelf a manifeſt Contradiction,
needs I hope no further Confutation.</p>
            <p>Now in order to anſwer your firſt Queſtion, you muſt
remember, that <hi>Magna Charta</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides, <hi>That no Freeman ſhall be
diſſeized of his Free-hold, put out of his Inheritance, or forejudged of
Life or Limb, but by Legal Proceſs, the Laws of the Land, and Judgement of
his Peers;</hi> and by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Branch, <hi>That the Kings Rights and
Priviledges ſhall be preſerved untouch'd.</hi> One of the chiefeſt, and
upon which all the reſt depend, as on a Corner-ſtone, is, <hi>the
Hereditarineſſe of the Monarchy,</hi> ſo that no attainder by Parliament,
or otherwiſe, ſhould hinder the Deſcent of the Crown upon the next of
Blood; the Laws ſuppoſing the King never dies, which he muſt do, if the
Empire were Elective: and to the obſervation of theſe Laws, on pain of
Damnation, the preſent and former Kings have all been ſworn: So that the
King having no power to act contrary to his Oath at Coronation, and the Laws in
being, and the two Houſes having none at all but what is derived from him,
'tis plain the next Heir cannot be put by the Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without great
impiety and violation of Juſtice. And this has been declared ſo in all
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Parliaments not aw'd by Uſurpers, as well as by the practice of
our Anceſtors. And that which moſt confirms it, is, That never any yet
claimed the Crown in Parliament, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Lineal Deſcent,
which was never allowed when falſe, but when there was not a power in the
true Owner equal to the Invader's. Nor does the King alone in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
lie under the obligation of Oaths; The Lords and Commons have not only bound
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>to
defend the true and lawful Heirs of the King, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the undoubted
Succeſſors, with their Lives and Fortunes to the Worlds end;</hi> but do
alſo ſwear as often as they meet, or take the Oaths of Allegeance and
Supremacy, to defend all the Priviledges, Rights, and Preheminences of the
Crown, (under which none can doubt, but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent in the Right Line is
included) againſt all Pretenders whatſoever, whether Forraign or
Domeſtick.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there are a ſort of Men, who, from the foregoing
Conſiderations, being conſcious they cannot maintain the Power of
Parliament in this particular, have recourſe to the Law of Nature, I will
give you a Scheme of that, even in their own Sence and Theorems. <hi>The Law of
Nature is co extended with the Power of Nature; there is therefore nothing
naturally unlawful, and every man, whether he be wiſe, or whether he be a
fool, is</hi> ſui juris. <hi>Every thing endeavours to conſerve it ſelf
within the State of Nature, and to be</hi> ſui juris, <hi>i. e.</hi> to do
what he will, to repel all Force, to live <hi>ex ingenio ſuo, i. e.</hi> to
be an enemie to every man but himſelf, if he contradicts his Will. <hi>Men
are lyable to ſeveral Paſſions,</hi> i. e. <hi>have ſeveral Appetites,
by which naturally they are engaged againſt one another; and by the Law of
Nature they inforce,</hi> i. e. <hi>they contend equally</hi> jure naturae,
which <hi>I</hi> Engliſh, <hi>by the Law of Power.</hi> One man is ſtronger
than another by force, and ſo compels him, who before was <hi>ſui
juris,</hi> to be <hi>alterius juri,</hi> when he hath him bound, diſarmed,
or takes away all his Power of offending, or holds him in fear <hi>or obliges
him by benefit, or expectation of benefit, by which last means he ſubjects
both his Body and his Mind, as long as his Fear or Hope lasts, but no longer:
By the former he ſubjects his Body only, which is the ſafer way.</hi>
Again, One man may be ſtronger than another by Wit, and ſo are men
ſubjected to be <hi>alterius juris,</hi> by Opinion, Religion, or
Superſtition, Errour and Deceit. Two then are ſtronger than one, and
therefore <hi>the more conſenting have the greater right of Nature against
the fewer diſsent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may urge, and compel, and deprive them of their
Natural Right, and, in brief, treat them as enemies.</hi> And becauſe no man
can ſecure himſelf againſt a whole World of ſingle men, who have every
one the ſame Right againſt me, that I alone have againſt every one, and
much leſs againſt a number joyned together; 'tis therefore neceſſary
for me, who elſe can have no ſecurity to enjoy what I have, nor probability
to acquire many of the Deſirables of Life, <hi>to aſſociate</hi> my
ſelf, and depart from ſo much of my natural Right, as prudence and reaſon
oblige me to do, which is <hi>pacto vivere,</hi> i. e. <hi>jus civitatis, the
Law, Right, or Power of the Commonwealth:</hi> So that I have henceforth no
more Right to the Law of Nature, than is allowed me, or not forbidden. I ſay,
<hi>not forbidden,</hi> becauſe, <hi>what is not forbidden, I retain.</hi>
And this is the Foundation of Laws;<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153272:5"/>and though a Law be
Poſitive, yet the Virtue of it is Negative, and as much as to ſay, <hi>You
ſhall not uſe your Liberty of Nature in this particular.</hi> By which 'tis
very evident, that after men have entred into Society, thoſe things that
before were lawful, ceaſe to be ſo any longer; Right, and Wrong, Juſt and
Unjuſt, depending on the Conceſſions, Covenants, and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the
Perſons thus combining into one Bodie. And therefore nothing is more
unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and fallacious than to aſſert, That the Power and original
Right of Nature for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or altering any Government, ſtill
continues, and may at pleaſure be reſumed by the major part, or their
Repreſentatives; whereas that Power is reſtrained, and can never more be
made uſe of, without every ſingle Perſons conſent in the whole
Community, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oſning the Bonds
of Society, and re-inſtating them in the condition of War and Miſery,
Madneſs and Folly. The ground of the miſtake muſt be Inadvertencie, or
Inconſideration, in not regarding, <hi>That promiſes once made can never be
broken, no not by the greateſt number, without the free conſent of every
individual party concerned.</hi> This Power of reſtraining the Right of
Nature, is Empire: If in one it is Monarchie, if in ſome it is
Ariſtocracie, if in the common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the People it is Democracie;
all theſe Governments are lawful, where they are Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. <hi>Now to
disturb or ruine any of them, is Rebellion, and returning to the state of
Nature, and utterly unlawful;</hi> which yet any man, or companie of men, may
do by the original Law of Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> by might and Power; but <hi>at
his or their peril under the impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Folly, of not obtaining his or
their End, of loſing the benefite of Society, and of being
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Enemies.</hi> Now,
becauſe men are not guided, or governed by Reaſon always, no man, or
companie of men are to be truſted to their own diſcretion, and the conduct
of their own Reaſon; for every mans Reaſon, is Reaſon to himſelf, but
the Reaſon of the Communitie is the Reaſon of State, not the Reaſon of
the man. And therefore, the Supreme is always entruſted with this Reaſon,
and in the Exerciſe of it ought to be ſecured by a tranſcendent Power, to
give Check to the pretentions of the Enemies of Society. This muſt be done
two ways: I. By aſſuring a ſtrength competent againſt any Attempts of
retrieving their original Right of Nature: 2. <hi>By</hi> an equal
Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and good Government; for, <hi>Res nolunt male
adminiſtrari.</hi> The end of Government is, That men may live together
unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the equal uſe of Civil Laws. The end of Religion is, to be
happy in the next World; and therefore ought not to interfere with Civil Laws,
or thoſe by which the good this Life is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated. But becauſe the Motives
to Obedience to thoſe Laws do very much depend upon the Rewards and
Expectations of a Future State, they are therefore neceſſarily conjoyned;
ſo that whatever Religion is eſtabliſhed by Law, becomes Law, and ought
not in prudence to be chang'd and diſturb'd. Whoever hath a private Religion
or Opinion, ſeing it is not more in our power to have <hi>mentem ſanam</hi>
than <hi>corpus ſanum,</hi> yet if the man be not mad, or injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he may
and ought to enjoy it freely without puniſhment, provided he do not violate
the peace of the City: If he do, 'tis nor Sincerity, but Hypocriſie; and
ſeeing there may be <hi>bona mens in malo articulo,</hi> all liberty ought to
be afforded, that can reaſonably &amp; modeſtly be claimed by any of
thoſe who pretend a tender Conſcience. Now if you conſider throwly
theſe Poſitions, you will find not onely the Reaſons of entring into
Society, but the Cauſes of its Continuance, and Decay fully aſſerted. The
Rules of Government are as demonſtrable, as any Mathematical Problems; and
where the Supreme is wiſe, there can be no Rebellion, or not dangerous; and
wherever there is, the Government is infirm and fooliſh. In order then to
your Queſtion, you muſt obſerve, That <hi>Power</hi> is an equivocal
Word, and is ſometime taken for the Right and Force of Nature, ſometimes
for the Right and Force of Laws. In the firſt ſenſe 'tis called
<hi>vis,</hi> or <hi>potestas;</hi> in the latter, <hi>jus,</hi> or
<hi>dominium.</hi> The firſt ſort of Power men in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety have
renounced, and cannot uſe without returning to the State of War, where every
man has as equal Right or Power over another, as another has over him. The
ſecond ſort of Power is that which the Laws of the Society warrant, and by
which 'tis ſaid, <hi>Illud tantum poſſumus, quod de jure
poſſumus.</hi> Now if we conſider the Power of Parliaments bounded by
Laws, in the letter ſenſe, 'tis plain they can have none to bar the Duke
from Succeſſion, becauſe the Laws Common and Statute leave them no ſuch
Power, and in Nature and Reaſon, after entring into<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153272:6"/>Society, they can exerciſe no more than is left them by the
Agreements of the Society. In the firſt ſenſe, 'tis true, they have power
to do what they pleaſe, as two is ſtronger then one: But then it muſt be
remembred, that the uſing that Power looſens the bond of the Commonwealth,
the whole having no more Right over <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> while
they break not the Laws of the Country, than <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>
had over all the reſt. If it were not ſo, there would be no Right nor Wrong
in the World, neither ſubſequent nor antecedent to Humane Conſtitutions;
Virtue and Viec would be but empty Names, Scar-crows for the Fools and the
Weak: For every thing would be lawful, that a man had force or ſtrength
enough to juſtifie. A Principle deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of Government and Society, of
Peace and Happineſſe. Everle Thief and Murderer, Robber and Traytor, if
ſucceſsful, being honeſt perſons, guilty of no Miſchiefs. Thus indeed
Vice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Virtue, <hi>Proſperum ſcelus virtus vocatur.</hi> This
therefore not being to be allowed among men, much leſſe Chriſtians, the
Parliament cannot juſtifie a Power of putting by the next Heir, by the
Conſtitutions of the Kingdom, nor by thoſe of <hi>nature;</hi> which allows
not the major part to have recourſe to natural Force or Liberty, without
leaving all the reſt of the Members to their choice of entring either into
none, or a new Form, or continuing under the old. And thoſe that aſſert
the Parliament may do what they pleaſe, know not what they ſay, if they
deny others the ſame freedom; and if they do, 'tis bidding all men
<hi>Draw,</hi> &amp; try who has the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Arm, and the longeſt
Sword, making Might or Power the onely Rule of Juſtice, and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of
Humane Actions. But this ſo dangerous miſtake is grounded upon not
conſidering, that what was lawful before I became a Member of the Society,
ceaſes to be ſo after. When a Bargain is once concluded between one man and
a thouſand, the thouſand cannot without injuſtice break the Agreement,
nor without folly expect the ſingle man will not take the firſt opportunity
to be reveng'd, and obliege them to their firſt Contract. And whether he
prove ſucceſsful or no, it will occaſion ſuch Miſchiefs &amp;
Calamities, that they will too late repent their Follies, and find no other
comfort, than the ſad one which this ſcrap of <hi>Latin</hi> affords,
<hi>Supplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſtultorum ſtultitia.</hi> But further, if you rightly
examine things, you will find, that the Lords onely act for themſelves, and
that the Commons of <hi>England</hi> do no otherwiſe repreſent the People
than as Attorneys, who, therefore are preſum'd limited to the firſt
Conſtitutions, and Fundamentals, that is, the Common Law, or <hi>Magna
Charta,</hi> whoſe Bounds if they exceed, they forfeit the Patent or
Commiſſion by which they act. This is agreeable to Reaſon, and the
pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Former Ages, when the Commons being ask'd their Conſents to new
Matters, went home and conſulted their Principles, and according to their
directions gave in their Anſwers, as you may find at large in the <hi>Rerum
Anglicarum Scriptores,</hi> and as in the preſent as well as ancient uſage
in the Dyets of <hi>Germany,</hi> and States of <hi>Holland.</hi> And thus it
was in the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> who, though they had the Supreme power as a
Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> yet in the making of any new Law, there was a
<hi>Rogatio Legis,</hi> an expoſing of it in Tables to the view of all for a
certain limited time, wherein if the meaneſt ſhewed Arguments why it
ſhould, it was wholly laid aſide. And ſo dangerous a thing have
Innovations in this ſort been accounted by the Ancients, that among the
<hi>Locrenſes,</hi> and other Commonwealths of <hi>Greece,</hi> new Laws were
propounded with Ropes about the propoſers Necks, ſubmitting themſelves to
the loſs of their Lives, if the propoſition were not approved by every
ſingle perſon. And in <hi>Poland,</hi> no King can be elected without the
conſent of every individual Elector. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in ſo material an
Inſtance, as the deſignation of a Supreme Governour, upon whom depends
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fates of Thouſands, no
majority, Parties, or Factions, ought to prevail. The ſame care have our
Anceſtors taken in the caſe of Jurors; concluding it neceſſary, for
deſpoiling a man of his Life or Fortune, to have the matter of Fact ſo
plain and conſpicuous, that it ſhould not be poſſible for any to doubt
or long diſpute it: And upon this reaſonable Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition it is, that
they are not allowed either meat or drink, or that eleven agreeing, while One
diſſents, ſhould make a Verdict. And can the publick Concern of the
Nation, of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the next of Blood from his Right to the Crown, be of
leſs moment? Conſider this in time, leſt hereafter by a dear bought
repentance, you confeſſe your fatal Errour. Beſides, the Commons do not
repreſent one ſixth of the Nation, their Electors being onely ſuch
free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153272:6"/>as are worth 40<hi>s.</hi> a year, or upwards,
together with the Freemen of Incorporated places; theſe are far ſhort of
the Body of the people; and for them to fetter the reſt, who have none or
leſs Eſtates, is to make themſelves Lords and Tyrants, and to the others
not Servants, but Slaves and Villains; a power unreaſonable, and therefore
not to be allowed by the Clergy, who, as ſuch, have no hand in the Election,
and are a conſiderable part of the People; nor by the Husband men and
Labourers, and many others, who, without Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom inhabite Corporations, who
bearing their proportion of the publick charge, are equally intituled to the
protection of the Laws, Free-born-Subjects, and therefore unask'd cannot be
preſumed to conſent to any alteration of Government either in the Form or
Perſon, by making an Hereditary Monarchy, Elective. Such a Power once
acknowledged, may after at pleaſure change it into Ariſtocracy, or
Democracy. Nor, in my opinion, is it a mean Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Commons,
being the Repreſentation of the whole People, That of 512. Forty ſhould be
enough to oblige the Conſent of all the others; That <hi>London</hi> ſhould
ſend but four, when an old Burrough with a Shepherd and a Dog does half as
many; and, That <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal,</hi> which in the Number of Shires is but the two
and fiftieth part, makes above an eleventh; and yet <hi>London,</hi> the
ſixth part of the Kingdom, but the 128. part of the whole Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.
Whoever weighs this Inequality, muſt find out a new ſignification of Words,
if he calls the Parliament <hi>the Repreſentative of all the Commons of
England.</hi> Let it be remembred, how eaſie it is to make a ſecond
<hi>Rump,</hi> by Cunning, and Addreſs, Threats and Tumults, to make the
Houſe ſo thin, that forty agreeing ſhall be ſtill the major Party; and
then ſee how far the Nation muſt conclude themſelves bound by their
Actings. One may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, all that Voted againſt the Act, and all, or
moſt that were abſent, will fight for his Title againſt whom it was made,
as well as all, or moſt of thoſe that: hold not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
repreſented; and what can be the iſſue of this, but a renewal of the
<hi>Yorkiſt</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castrian</hi> Quarrel, in which was ſpilt the
blood of 20000, beſides that of ſeveral Kings and Princes, and Nobles
without number? And yet it appears in Story, That the Right Heir was never kept
out beyond the ſecond Deſcent, nor that ever any Uſurper, Though Armed
with Power, claimed the Crown, but by pretending to be of the Right Line; nor
did the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ever conſent, out when aw'd by Fear, and a vaſt Army.
As for the Act 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> the beſt Lawyers will tell you, 'tis now
out of doors, made in defence of a poſſeſſor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Title, againſt
the rightful Heir, at that time excluded for Reaſons as obvious as tedious
here to be mentioned, but after joyfully received and ſolemniz'd in
Parliament, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> and Obedience promiſed to him and his Heirs for
ever; ſo that now, in the opinions of many, that Statute ought no more to be
urged, than that which made <hi>Oliver</hi> Protector, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded his
preſent Majeſty and his Line.</p>
            <p>To allow the Parliament ſo Deſpotick a Power, is to ſubmit
at preſent, and make our ſelves obnoxious to unaccountable miſeries
hereafter. What ſhall hinder a Parliament, who at pleaſure makes every
thing lawful or unlawful, as they are aw'd by a ſtrong hand, or left at
libertie by a weak, to do any thing, though never ſo extravagant; to ſell
the Kingdom to the <hi>French,</hi> or any rich enough to make the purchaſe?
I confeſſe, I think it a hard pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition (and that which makes the
Government of a ſingle man, though Tyrannical, more tolerable than this of
ſo many) That the major part of 700. as they may be ordered of leſs than
100. who as Commons have no inderivative Power, &amp; are only called to
adviſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate with the Prince, as Counſellors, ſhould make that
lawful that could not be done ſo without their Conſents, and me a Rebel for
reſiſting, though I have the greateſt part of the Nation on my ſide,
and my Actions warranted by all thoſe that are called Fundamental, and held
ſacred, and inviolable by <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> as our Bibles are by all
<hi>Protestants.</hi> He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members <hi>England</hi> has been given by a
King to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and offer'd to the <hi>Turk,</hi> and that a bold
&amp; reſolute <hi>Prince</hi> has humbled Parliaments, as much as ever a
weak and gentle has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted them, ought not to think it impoſſible, but
that the <hi>Parliament</hi> may one time or other be wrought to ſell, or
inſlave the Peoples Libertie: For, a worthy Author has it, <hi>Nothing but a
Parliament can deſtroy a Parliament;</hi> and we know there have been that
deſerved no other Titles, than of <hi>Indoctum &amp; Inſanum
Parliamentum.</hi> I ſhould not wonder, that men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153272:7"/>rather to quit their Country, than yield it to an Arbitrary
power, or any pretence whatſoever, with the bold <hi>Romans</hi> Farewell
applied to this Kingdom, <hi>Vale venalis civitas mox peritura, ſi emptorem
inveneris.</hi> I need not put you in mind of <hi>Penſioners,</hi> or tell
you a mercenary <hi>parliament</hi> is an acry Notion: <hi>What has been, may
be again.</hi> I reverence a well-conſtituted <hi>Parliament</hi> as much as
any man: and look upon it as an excellent preſervative of Juſtice and
Liberty; yet I am not ſo fond of the Name, as to make it an Idol: 'tis not at
all improbable, but that it may be ſo managed, as to become the Inſtrument
of the peoples Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and the Princes Tyranny; and therefore, I hold it no
more lawful to aſcribe Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, or Infallibilitie in all Determinations
to a <hi>Parliament,</hi> than to a <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Council;</hi> the one
is not more circumſcribed and bound up by <hi>Scripture</hi> and
<hi>Apoſtolick Traditions,</hi> than is the other by the <hi>Fundamental Laws
of the Land,</hi> (ſuch there are in every Country, as <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta</hi>
is in this) by <hi>Nature,</hi> and by <hi>Reaſon:</hi> All which tell us,
<hi>That no ſingle man in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity is to be put by his Right or Property by
any ſubſequent Law againſt his own Conſent: and that if he be, he is at
liberty to regain it any how, by force, or by violence, without the leaſt
imputation of Wrong, or Injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for your ſecond Queſtion, you will find its Anſwer
eaſily deducible from what has been ſaid already; For, allowing that the
<hi>Parliament</hi> have power (which yet without every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual perſons
Conſent they cannot have, either by Nature, or their own Conſtitutions) to
alter the Succeſſion; yet no motives can be ſufficient to induce men in
their ſenſes to ſuch an Act, but plain tranſgreſſions and
violations of the Laws in being; nothing elſe being a Crime, or penal. The
Apoſtle tells us, <hi>If there had been no Law, there would have been no
ſin;</hi> and that <hi>though ſin was in the world before, yet till after
the Law, it neither was nor could be imputed:</hi> i. e. <hi>Yeſterday I
killed my neighbour, but that was not unlawful, conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not
puniſhable, becauſe the Act againſt it was but this day enjoyned, and
every man is left to the uſe of his natural power, in ſuch instances as the
Laws do not reſtrain.</hi> This is ſo plain a truth in all Countries, where
Men are not govern'd like Beaſts, that 'tis not onely folly but madneſs to
aſſert the contrary: The Abettors are not to be convinc'd by Arguments and
Reaſons, but by <hi>Hellebore</hi> and <hi>Bedlam.</hi> Now, there being no
Laws in being, that enjoyn the Heir of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to believe
as the Church of <hi>England,</hi> his departure from that to any other Church
can be no Argument for his Diſinheriſon. But the other part, <hi>his giving
life, and birth to the plot,</hi> is of another conſideration, and, if true,
deſerved not only his being put by the Crown, but his Life: And therfore, I
conceive, if that had been evident, he had not eſcap'd ſo eaſily, nor
indeed could he, without the imputation of great partiality and injuſtice
upon the Houſe of Commons: No mean Argument of the Duk's Innocence to any
conſidering perſon. For, if they proceeded ſo far upon an Illogical
Conſequence, or unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Propoſition, to wit, <hi>That his going
over to the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>muſt have given birth and life to the
Helliſh Plot,</hi> what would they not have done farther, if they could have
prov'd, <hi>that he was indeed the Author?</hi> which he muſt have been of
neceſſity, if he <hi>gave birth and life to it.</hi> Now leſt the World
ſhould take every thing done by any <hi>Factious number</hi> to be the Act of
all <hi>the Commons,</hi> much leſs of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſo
defame the Juſtice and Integrity of the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> and leſt
the people ſhould believe whatever they aſſert, as Oraculous, as the
Vulgar do of things in <hi>Print;</hi> 'tis neceſſary to examine this
matter very narrowly, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how they came by this Diſcovery, or why,
if it were real, they inflicted no ſeverer a puniſhment than an Act, that
the beſt Lawyers tell us would have been of no force, had it paſſ'd even
the <hi>Royal Aſsent;</hi> which I cannot think it ever would, becauſe
contrary to the King's Oath at Coronation, &amp; his Promiſe &amp;
Reſolution declar'd even in that very <hi>Parliament,</hi> where many doubt
its paſſing the third time among the <hi>Commons,</hi> and none diſpute
but that the <hi>Lords</hi> would have rejected it upon the <hi>firſt
reading.</hi> The grand Diſcoverer, Dr. <hi>Oats,</hi> has not accuſ'd his
R. H. but, one the contrary, in publick and private, acquitted him from any
guilt, or knowledge; as, beſide his printed <hi>Narrative</hi> and
<hi>Depoſitions</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> may be made out by Perſons of
unqueſtionable Honour. Could then a Vote make matters of Fact, Truth or
Falſ-hood? That depends upon natural and eternal Cauſes, and Connexions of
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable Principles. Surely no, nor would any man in his Senſe have given
the more credit,<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153272:7"/>though it had paſſ'd 500000 Votes
inſtead of 500. If twenty Colledges of <hi>Virtuoſo's,</hi> or
<hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamites,</hi> ſhould conſpire to vote the old
<hi>Philoſopher</hi> in the right, who every where aſſerted <hi>Snow was
black,</hi> yet could they not perſuade one Plowman to disbelieve his
Senſes, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to ſo ridiculous an Opinion. And as to Capt.
<hi>Bedlow,</hi> (and upon theſe two the whole Hinge of the <hi>Plot</hi>
does turn, for the reſt came in but <hi>in ſubſidiam probationis</hi>) he
pretended at firſt to know no more than the inhumane Murder of Sir
<hi>Edmondbury Godſrey;</hi> and yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he became more knowing after,
he never accus'd his R. H. which he wold certainly have done, had he found one
probable Circumſtance; even upon his Death he acquitted him. Yet, to ſay
Truth, his accuſation wold have been of leſs credit, for his having been
ſo miſtaken in his main Diſcovery, as to be contradicted by
<hi>Prance;</hi> the reaſon, I ſuppoſe, why no <hi>Narrative</hi> in
Capt. <hi>Bedlow's</hi> Name, was ever publiſh'd. Read Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> his
<hi>Depoſitions,</hi> and you will find the D. was to run the ſame fate of
his Brother, <hi>(whoſe ſacred Life God long preſerve)</hi> if he would
not approve of all their Villanies, and after his Majeſties Murder accept the
Crown as Feudatory from the <hi>Pope:</hi> And, without diſpute the villanous
Contrivers of the Plot would have ſpared neither: which is plain by Mr.
<hi>Oates</hi> his aſſerting upon Oath in the Name of the Jeſuits, that
no good was ever to be expected from the Race of the <hi>Stewarts,</hi> with
other Reflections on the R. Family, with ſubmiſſion not fit to have been
publiſhed: And further, that they had reſolved, notwithſtanding his Love
to their Religion, not to truſt him with a Secret, his great affection for
his Brother would perſwade him to reveal. It is then impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, he
could give Birth and Life to a Plot, to which he never was privy? as for
<hi>Colman's</hi> Letters, in my Lord <hi>Danby's</hi> Words, the beſt
evidence we yet have of the Plot, they were not writ by the D's allowance or
conſent, nor do they ſpeak of introducing <hi>Popery</hi> otherwiſe than
by gaining an Indulgence, and that by a Parliament. Beſides, 'tis
notoriouſly known he was offered his Pardon and large Rewards, if he would
confeſſe the Plot. And 'tis ſenſeleſs to imagine, (none can, but an
unthinking Crowd) that he would not ſpeak a Truth to ſave his Life, at
leaſt not damn his Soul by dying with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in his Mouth (after which nor
previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to it, there could be no Abſolution) but to the laſt
notwithſtanding the repeated offers of Pardon and Reward, he proteſted his
Ignorance and Innocency.</p>
            <p>Oh, but, ſay ſome, how then could the Commons proceed as they
did? Why, perhaps the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſher of that deſigned Bill abuſes them; but
if he did not, they do, who conclude the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part conſented to it. Thoſe
that did, may be ſuppoſed hurryed on by miſguided Zeal; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or
prejudice, impoſed upon by Suggeſtions, as agreable to the King's
pleaſure to baniſh him for ever by Law, who in Obedience went into a
voluntary exile for a ſeaſon; If this be not, I confeſſe I am at a
loſſe for the Reaſon: But of this they were ſoon convinc'd by his
Majeſty's Speech to the contrary. Beſides, it had been but equal to have
given his R. H. liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to make his Defence; to condemn a Man unheard is no
where practiſed, where there is the leaſt ſhadow of Government. The Laws
of God, and of Nations forbid, nay, make it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Society, to
hang a Man firſt, and convict him after, or, to puniſh any one <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſt facto.</hi> My Lord
<hi>Strafford's</hi> Caſe was never to be brought into preſident, and if
that were not ſufficient, the whole proceedings by Act of Parliament ſince
his Majeſties Reſtauration were condemn'd, as illegal and contrary to all
Morality. And would not the D's Caſe have been juſt the ſame? Do you but
make it your own, and you will be of that Opinion.</p>
            <p>Whence I conclude, that the Reaſons on which the late Houſe of
Commons proceeded againſt the D. were inſufficient, becauſe not only not
warranted, but contrary to the Laws in being, as well as to thoſe of Nature,
and all Societies under Heaven. And now I come to your third Queſtion, what
dangers the Nation may be under in caſe the Crown deſcends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Popiſh
Succeſſor, or more particularly upon his R. H?</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which we muſt conſider, that dangers to any
Country are Forraign or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick, Invaſions from abroad, or Encroachments
a home. Againſt the former, every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is in danger, be the Prince of any
or no Religion, and therefore the People are oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be always on their
Guard. Againſt the latter the hazard lies in the Princes neglect, or breaking
of the bounds of his Subjects Liberty, Property, and Religion: and ſince the 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153272:8"/>ſafety of all Princes depends upon the contrary, why a
Popiſh one ſhould offer it more then another, I cannot comprehend; and more
particularly why his R. H. ſhould deſign it, is not at all likely, if we
examine either the influence Popery can have over the Government, or conſider
impartially the D's Character.</p>
            <p>Government was firſt framed for the good of Mankind in this
Life, without any regard to another, and depended upon a due and equal
adminiſtration of juſtice in the Governour, and Obedience in the governed.
This was long obſerved in the World before Religion entered, eſpecially
Chriſtianity, which all allow, neither did, nor could alter the Laws of the
City, or Common-wealth. <hi>Evangelium non abolet politias</hi> is every where
an allowed Maxim, drawn from our Saviour's own Words; <hi>Friend, who made me a
Ruler or judge among you? The Law is open, and by that the controverſies
between you and your Brother are to be decided.</hi> He came not to diſturb,
but to enlarge, and confirm the peace of the City, and his Laws conſidered
a-part are as conſiſtent with thoſe of a Kingdom, as the by-Laws of any
Corporation within a greater State. He declared his Kingdom was not of this
World, and therefore could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to alter the grounds of Government and
Obedience, which are one and the ſame in all Countries whether Chriſtian or
<hi>Pagan,</hi> founded upon ſelf-intereſt and preſervation, and
continued by mutual Relation of Love and Duty, Protection and Obedience;
things, that truly conſidered, can never be altered by the ſuper-induction,
or change of any new or old Religion. If then Chriſtianity make no
alteration, 'tis impoſſible the ſub-diviſions, or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sects
ſhould. So that whatever Opinion, either King or Subject be, in point of
Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Popiſh or Proteſtant; <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Calviniſt,
Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> the ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment peace and
quiet, Liberty and Property may be ſecured and enjoy'd, and the end of
Religion too, eternal Salvation; this depending on moral Duties, and Conformity
to the Laws of the Land; our Saviour having threatned Damnation to thoſe who
reſiſt the higher Powers; the greateſt of puniſhments being appointed
both by the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Law to Rebellion, called by the firſt,
the Sin of Witchraft, and in the laſt, a fighting againſt God
himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now all Laws that concern our temporal eſtate being made in the
times of Popery, I cannot find why they ſhould be changed by a Popiſh
Monarch; nor how, without a change or violation the Subjects can ſuffer. As
for the Laws that eſtabliſhed the Proteſtant, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the
Popiſh Religion, they cannot be otherwiſe altered but by an equal power,
with that from whence they had their Being, King and Parliament, who agreeing
can by a change no more prejudice the publick in order to Heaven, than they did
before; that being only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental and extrinſecal to the Subſtance of
Religion, by which alone, and not by Forms or Ceremonies Men are to be ſaved;
every Country making differences in ſuch things according to the ſeveral
intereſt of States, or humours of the people; as in <hi>England</hi> the
Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is tempered by the King's holding the Ballance, between the power
of Lords and Commons, and that upon the taking away of either, the Government
muſt be deſtroyed: ſo the Religion of <hi>England,</hi> or indeed of any
Kingdom, where there are ſeveral Sects, ſeem only to be preſerved by
fixing a Ballance, which taken away, muſt be the ruine of the whole; and
therefore undeniable policy will tell us, that the Epiſcopal legal Government
is no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be preſerved, but by equally indulging the
Non-Conformiſts and the Papiſts, for to ſuppreſs both is now
impracticable, and to ſuppreſſe one alone will be found impolitick. A
Truth grounded upon the preſent State of <hi>Europe,</hi> where, while
<hi>England</hi> kept the Ballance between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi>
the univerſal Monarchy was a Dream, or groundleſſe Fancie: but that being
removed, 'tis impoſſible, if two or three Martial and prudent Princes
happen ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively to govern <hi>France,</hi> but that before imaginary
Empire will really fall to the Lot of that Nation, unleſſe all the other
States joyn againſt it, and give our Country the power it enjoyed, when
<hi>Spain</hi> was an equal Match in the Contention. For my own part,
<hi>I</hi> ſee nothing to be dreaded in caſe of a Popiſh Succeſſor,
becauſe he alone cannot alter the Laws, nor the Religion; nor can he the
execution, ſince that is out of his, and in the hands of ſuch as are not
only ſworn to it, but upon failure lyable to great Penalties and Forfeiture,
not<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153272:8"/>only to the Prince, who poſſibly might, but to the
Informer, who cannot be ſuppoſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his proportion. And
conſidering that the Laws in being have entruſted the executive power of
the Militia by Sea and Land, and of diſtributive Juſtice in Courts, and all
Offices of Truſt, as well in the Country, as about the Princes Perſon, and
the power of making, and altering Laws in the Hands of Men of Anti-popiſh
Principles, I cannot apprehend, why we ſhould conceive any danger from a
Princes enjoying to himſelf any Heterodox Opinion whatever. For to think he
would impoſe them upon his Subjects; is to conclude him not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprudent,
but diſtracted; ſince it would be to create himſelf diſturbance,
without the leaſt proſpect of advantage: for what does he get or looſe by
their being of this, or that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion? His Good, his Wealth, his Glory,
his Honour, and Security, conſiſts in their conformity to the
eſtabliſhed Government, and for their future Happineſſe he cannot as a
Prince be ſolitcious; 'tis out of his <hi>Province,</hi> and now out of
Faſhion for Kings to be <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi> This then
would be folly, and to purſue it would be madneſs, becauſe it would be to
oppoſe his ſingle ſtrength, (for in this caſe he would ſtand alone)
to the united force of Lords and Commons, and the whole Body of the People. And
who knows not, that in this Senſe <hi>Dominium fundatur in voluntatibus
hominum.</hi> For without an Army, and a very great one, he could not
compaſſe his impertinent project, this Army he could not raiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a
vaſt Treaſure; this Treaſure he cannot have but from his own people in
Parliament, who will not give it to their prejudice. For out of Parliament he
cannot have enough, even for his ordinary Expence, much leſſe for the
defence of the Kingdom againſt forraign At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; becauſe upon the death
of the preſent, the following Succeſſor will find ſo much fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len off,
that there will not be left one third of the preſent inſufficient Revenue
for all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Uſes of the Crown: An Argument that alone may convince
the ſober and unbyaſs'd, that be he of what perſwaſion ſoever, he
muſt of neceſſity comply with his Parliament who can't be ſuppoſ'd
neglectful of the great Concern of <hi>Religion.</hi> And to think that the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> at home, or abroad will give it, is Folly, or
Inconſideration. Thoſe at home could not by the ſale of all their
Fortunes make the Fond; that can never be ſuppoſed by men in their wits:
nor indeed can I ſee, why they ſhould contribute at all, ſince their gain
by offices, of which they are now incapable, would be but advantagious to
ſome; and why ſhall the whole be at a loſſe for the profit of a few,
&amp; that uncertain? Beſides, that party is now more a Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by freedom
from offices of Charge and Trouble, than they could then be by the partial
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Employments. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> abroad will leſs find their
Accompt; for Princes of all Religions, and the only preſent rich and powerful
one of <hi>That,</hi> expends his Money for Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Glory, leaving, as he
ought, the Heavenly to the Spiritual Princes. Theſe all are, ever were, and
will be, ſuch Lovers of Wealth, Pomp, and Grandour, as not to beſtow it in
the purchaſe of Heaven, which they know is not to be bought for Silver or for
Gold. The <hi>Pope</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining <hi>Peter-pence</hi> could not invite him,
if he had the Sum, for if you compute that, you will find it a Trifle, 6666,
reckoning it after the way of the preſent Chimney-money, ſet for 160 odd
thouſand pounds, at two ſhillings a Chimney; whereas that was only a peny a
Houſe, not a peny a Chimney, as in this Caluclation is allow'd, when Houſes
are much more than in thoſe days. And for the Firſt-fruits and Tenths, they
are no leſſe inconſiderable. For Indulgences, Appeals, and the
conſequent Charges, they are trivial and accidental, and go not into the
<hi>Pop's,</hi> but into particular Officers pockets. Beſides, no one
<hi>Pope</hi> can hope to ſee ſuch a Deſign effected; and the Nephews and
Nieces will prevent their converting their Riches to the advantage of the
Succeſſors. And as for the Church or Abby-Lands, they could not on this
accompt be of any moment, ſince if reſtor'd to the Church which would be
uncertain, as the effect of War, they would fall into the hands of Clergy-men,
who have nothing before hand to contribute.</p>
            <p>Now conſidering that the late rais'd Army, under 30000 men, put
the King to the charge of more than a Million; how many Millions, think you,
muſt be requiſite for a much greater Army, neceſſary for ſo great a
Deſign; when the Oppoſition will be ſtrong and laſting, the very Lifted
Millitia being above 160000? And ſuppoſing that all the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms would become Voluntiers in this extravagant Expedition,
the whole would be ſtill as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionat, and as unliklely to prevail,
as an Army of Pigmies, with Spears of Bulruſhes,<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153272:9"/>mounted on
Crans, againſt an Army of Gyants, riding on Elephants, and every way well
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for War.</p>
            <p>In the year 1672. (and they cannot ſince be much encreas'd) the
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> upon a Survey of them, <hi>Conformists</hi> and
<hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> ſeverally, were found throughout <hi>England</hi>
to be under 27000. Men, Women, and Children: In <hi>Scotland</hi> the
diſproportion is greater on the <hi>proteſtant</hi> ſide; in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> on the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> Yet by a <hi>Medium</hi> of all
three, there would be 203. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to one <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
What then can be dreaded from them, though asſiſted with an Army of
profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat Hirelings, (for none elſe would fight to deſtroy Religion, and
enſlave their Country) and a Prince of their own Perſwaſion, whoſe
Example could win but on the mean and baſe, the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and mercenary
Courtiers, to hold with him, as with other Kings, their Necks awry? So
inconſiderable a Number could not ſhock the main Body of the People,
ſighting not as the others, for Opinion, or for Pay, but further, for
Liberty, Property, Religion, and Eſtate; of which being poſſeſt, though
the others were equal in Numbers, theirs would be the advantage, according to
that Rule, <hi>Milior eſt conditio posſidentis.</hi> And indeed,
conſidering the Athelſtical bent and humour of the Nation, whoſe Religion
is generally in their Mouths only, and not in their Hearts, <hi>I</hi> am apt
to conclude, the great Heat and Contention is founded upon the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
of the loſs of Church and Abby-Lands, not of <hi>proteſtantiſm;</hi> and
the rather, becauſe it is urged, <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Ecoleſiae:</hi>
The Maxim is <hi>&amp; Regi;</hi> and yet we find, though moſt of the
Lordſhips of <hi>England</hi> belonged formerly to the King, they are now
poſſeſt by others without danger of reaſſumption, and yet even that
has been practiſed in former Kings Reigns, and adviſed by parliaments who
al ways reputed them unalienable. And yet why we ſhould now be more
ſollicitous for fear of the Church, than of the King, I cannot underſtand;
ſince either preſcription, or their own Conſent, lies againſt both, and
that even in the infancy of the <hi>proteſtant Religion,</hi> upon the return
of <hi>Popery</hi> by parliament, the <hi>Pope</hi> did in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s
Reign, by his Legat Cardinal <hi>Poole,</hi> confirm to the Laity the Temporal
poſſesſions of the Clergy. And can any one imagine that how, when a
contrary Religion is of ſo long ſtanding, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors as far
exceeding the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in number, as they did then the
<hi>Proteſtants,</hi> a parliament would be kinder? Earthly Intereſt will
ever weigh more than Heavenly; the World being now ſo much enlightned with
Knowledge and Letters, beyond its former Experience, when not only Salvation,
but Wiſdom, hung upon the Lips of the prieſts, it be will be imposſible
for men to be perſwaded, even upon their Death-beds, to beſtow all for the
gaining of Heaven. The Statute of <hi>Mortmain</hi> was made in the height of
<hi>Popery,</hi> and none but Fools can ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed
upon, that a Statute of Reſtitution could be posſible in the Meridian of a
contrary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. This is well known to the leading and conſidering men;
who having Deſigns upon great Offices and preferments in the State, make the
Care of the Church a pretence only to their Ambition. 'Tis notoriouſly
evident, That no men were more violent for the general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, nay for
<hi>Popery,</hi> in 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. (not to
mention their before breaking the Triple League, and entring into an Alliance
with <hi>France</hi>) than thoſe who now are accounted the only Lovers of an
<hi>Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> A
Reſtitution of the Great Seal, or a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers White Staff; a
Diamond-hilted Sword, or being a Publick Miniſter, might perſwade the
ſame Perſons to act again as arbitrariouſly as before, ſet up
<hi>France</hi> and run down <hi>Holland,</hi> with a <hi>delenda eſt
Carthago.</hi> Good God! how ſtrange it is, that men who changed with every
Wind as that of their own Private, not their Countries Intereſt, blew; or
ſome younger Spirits influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by their Precepts &amp; Examples, in hopes
to make new, or retrive crack'd Fortunes, ſhould ride and hurry the Nation to
ſo much Heat and Paſſion, as endangers our utter ruine and
deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, either from Inteſtine Diviſions, or Forreign Invaſions!
Conſider this in time, before you are bemir'd and bewitch'd by any <hi>Will
o'th' Wiſp,</hi> who now leads you aſtray, and will certainly leave you in
the lurch, when he has gain'd the Point he drives at. Judge of future by former
Actions, and remember, if we muſt have any, <hi>That the old is better than
any new Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh, but</hi> (ſay ſome) <hi>If we have a Popiſh
Succeſſor, he will be the worst of Tyrants, being oblig'd</hi> (ſays the
Author of the <hi>Few Words among many</hi>) <hi>to extirpate his Proteſtant
Subjects, under the pain of Excommunication &amp; Damnation, &amp; that by
vertue of the Council of</hi> Lateran. An Aſſertion very groundleſs,
whether you conſider at large the Princes Intereſt, with which ſuch a
Practice<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153272:9"/>is incompatible, his being <hi>a King,</hi>
depending upon his Subjects; and a <hi>powerful one</hi> upon their Multitude,
Strength, and Riches: or if you conſider the Influence <hi>Christianity</hi>
it ſelf has upon the Civil Magiſtrate, or the particular Obligations of
this pretended Decree; Concerning which, you are to know, that this
<hi>Council</hi> is not eſteem'd <hi>General,</hi> nor the Decrees of this
(whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected by <hi>Canus</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) nor of <hi>any
Council,</hi> eſteem'd <hi>infallible,</hi> or obligatory in point of
<hi>Diſcipline,</hi> where they are not receiv'd and corroborated by the
Temporal Prince, who has the power of rejecting all or what part he thinks fit
of ſuch <hi>Decrees;</hi> as appears not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>this,</hi> but in that
of <hi>Trent,</hi> which is not <hi>univerſally received</hi> either in
<hi>France</hi> or <hi>Germany.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, theſe few that own <hi>this
Council,</hi> ſay it was never deſign'd againſt <hi>Sovereign Independent
Princes,</hi> nor was it ever practiſed out of <hi>Italy:</hi> So that why it
ſhould be dreaded in <hi>England</hi> cannot be found reaſonable, ſince
at this day in <hi>France, Germany,</hi> and <hi>other Countries,</hi> where
the <hi>main Body</hi> of the People is <hi>Popiſh, Proteſtants</hi> are
permitted <hi>their Freedoms,</hi> and <hi>their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</hi> A ſufficient
Argument, that <hi>Popiſh Princes</hi> fear no ſuch Sentence from
<hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Council.</hi> In ſome places of <hi>Germany,</hi> the
people are governed ſucceſſively by <hi>Popiſh</hi> &amp;
<hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> by <hi>Calvinists,</hi>
further aſunder than <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>Papist,</hi> without
inconvenience or diſturbance, taking their turns morning and afternoon in the
publick Churches; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the differences in Speculative
matters, nor poſſible to be avoided, live together as they ought in the
Union of <hi>Charity,</hi> the only <hi>bond of perfection,</hi> and Badge of
<hi>true Chriſtianity.</hi> So that <hi>Papiſts</hi> may be <hi>good
Kings,</hi> and <hi>good Subjects,</hi> as they are <hi>de facto,</hi> and have
been, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be again. And to ſhew how little <hi>particular
Opinions</hi> can alter the Duties of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and
<hi>Subjection,</hi> let it be remembred; That in the King of <hi>France</hi>
his Deſcent upon <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and in the time of his whole War with
<hi>that State,</hi> he could never get a <hi>Popiſh Spy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I am not ignorant the Perſecutions of Queen
<hi>Mary</hi> will be urged, though imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently; for beſides that the odds
was then on the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſide, yet in her Six years Reign as
<hi>Speed</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi> tell us, there were but 277 put to death, and
of theſe above 200 profligate Perſons, all dying by the <hi>Law,</hi> then,
and <hi>ſeveral Ages before</hi> in being, <hi>De Haretico comburendo,</hi>
by which ſeveral ſuffer'd in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s and King
<hi>Jame</hi>'s days for <hi>Arianiſm</hi> ſince abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated. So that, as
the caſe now ſtands in <hi>England,</hi> none can ſuffer as
<hi>Hereticks,</hi> till ſome <hi>new Law</hi> be firſt made, and that, you
know, muſt be by <hi>Force,</hi> or <hi>Parliament.</hi> The firſt is
ſhewn <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,</hi> and the latter <hi>improbable:</hi> Yet if
ſuch an Act paſsd, it muſt be eſteem'd conſonant to the deſires of
the <hi>whole Nation.</hi> So that the <hi>Martyrs</hi> of Queen
<hi>Mary</hi>'s days can no more be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>ſuch,</hi> than thoſe
who have ſuffer'd ſince the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> both being puniſh'd
<hi>juſtly,</hi> according to the <hi>Laws in being.</hi> Theſe laſt are
reckoned 170 in the ſpace of eighteen Mouths; of which, 147 ſtarved and
died in Priſon, and 23. executed, to every of whom Pardon and Reward was
offer'd, would they but confeſs themſelves guilty, and make a Diſcovery;
beſides five ſince condemned, and many more fled, ſtarving and begging in
other Countries. And here I confeſs my amazement and wonder, that ſo many
<hi>Lay-men</hi> and <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> Learned and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate, ſhould all
continue obſtinate in the <hi>denial</hi> of this <hi>damnable and helliſh
Popiſh Plot,</hi> when the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> own'd that cruel one of
the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can the Objection be leſs trivial of <hi>the hazard to the
Kings Sacred Life, while a Papiſt is to ſucceed;</hi> ſince a
<hi>Clement</hi> or a <hi>Raviliac</hi> is not more eaſily found among
<hi>them,</hi> than a <hi>Poltrot</hi> or an <hi>Andelot</hi> among the
<hi>Hugonots</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> But it is no greater
diſparagement to have ſingle Inſtances of Wickedneſs in a
<hi>Soceity,</hi> than to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that there was a
<hi>Judas</hi> in the number. 'Tis much more eaſie for <hi>Papists</hi> to
give, than to receive upon this account a <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for an
<hi>Oliver.</hi> They can not only return the number of
<hi>Aſſaſſins,</hi> but in ſtead of a few <hi>private ones;</hi>
ſhew them many <hi>publick Executioners of Kings and Princes,</hi> and in
ſtead of <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Aſſerters</hi> of the <hi>King-killing and
Depoſing Doctrines,</hi> as <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>La Forest,</hi> (who yet
do it but Problematically, and are with their Books cenſured and condemned by
the Eight Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of <hi>France,</hi> and the General of the
<hi>Jeſuits</hi> Order, and the whole Body of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> and
expreſly forbidden by the univerſally receiv'd <hi>Council of Conſtance,
Seſſ.</hi> 5.) I wiſh there could not be found whole Shoals of the
<hi>Reformed</hi> that avow thoſe <hi>Antichriſtian Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> not
only abroad, but in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland. Baxter,</hi> yet alive,
has never recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Tenets of his <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> not his owning,
in his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> his <hi>not finding upon the<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153272:10"/>ſtricteſt examination, to have done amiſs, in fomenting the late
Rebellion.</hi> I need not menti <hi>Outlandiſh Names</hi> of <hi>Calvin,
Beza, Paraeus, &amp;c.</hi> nor thoſe of <hi>Scotland, Knox, Bu chann
&amp;c.</hi> a Page would not contain all <hi>Miltons Engliſt Tutors</hi> and
<hi>Scolars</hi> in this particular, whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>Treaſon
and Rebellion,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Devotion</hi> is all <hi>Cheat and
Hypocriſie,</hi> and who are ineed ſo much the worſe and more dangerous
<hi>Jeſuits,</hi> as their Doctrines are in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> &amp; openly
maintained, whilſt the other publickly diſavow what they are accus'd of.
Thoſe all with one voice ſay, <hi>Dominion is jure divino;</hi> the others
ſay, <hi>'tis founded in Grace, and deriv'd from the People in trust, who
upon male adminiſtration may reſume their first Grant, dethrone and murder
their Sovereign, in spite of all the obligations of Oaths and Promiſes of
Faith and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> Now though it's poſſible both Parties may be
miſtaken, yet I am ſure the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Errour is on the ſafeſt
ſide for Princes. Conſider, Sir, ſeriouſly, and tell me, if you find
not of the two, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of <hi>Glaſcow</hi> and
<hi>Geneva</hi> more pernicious to Peace and Government, than thoſe of
<hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>St. Omers:</hi> Compare their Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es and their Principles, and try whether the
<hi>Paris</hi> Maſſacre of 40000, by <hi>D'avila,</hi> and as is plain in
Story, a politick Stratagem, be not ſeventy times exceeded by the Warr of
<hi>that Country</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> to name no more, upon the ſcore
of <hi>Reformation:</hi> Whether the much-nois'd Numbers ſlain in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> computed by the Ingenious and Learned Sir <hi>William
Petry,</hi> on both ſides, during the whole Rebellion, not above 36000, in a
conquer'd Country, ſet on foot for their <hi>Liberty and Eſtates,</hi> not
for <hi>Religion,</hi> be not far outdone by the late <hi>Rebellion of
Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> contriv'd and carried on by the <hi>Godly party.</hi> This was
not <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Method of planting the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> 'tis the
<hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> and not <hi>that of the fleſh,</hi> that muſt
propagate <hi>Religion;</hi> yet excepting our own Country, where it came not
in dry-ſhod, have not the Reformers every where waded deep in Blood in
oppoſition to popery? I need not inſtance, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are obvious, and
'tis an undeniable Truth, <hi>that there has been ten times more War and Bloud
ſhed, on the ſcore of Religion ſince</hi> Luther <hi>and</hi> Calvin's
<hi>time, then was in all the parts of</hi> Europ <hi>before, while</hi> popery
<hi>was at the higheſt.</hi> But beſides all this, the Vote of the late
<hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> has moſt certainly ſecured on that ſide all
danger to the King's Sacred Perſon, <hi>Whom God long preſerve;</hi> for if
now any ſhould be ſo mad, as to be Authors of ſo great an Impiety,
conſidering the vaſt inequalities of their Numbers, they could not expect
leſs then the loſs of their own Lives, and of the whole party, &amp;
therefore by that Vote they are not only charmed into Loyalty, if otherwiſe
diſpoſed, but qualified to guard the King's Perſon, if admitted, from the
attempts of any other Conſpirators; ſo that their mutual ſafeties depend
upon each other. And therefore it were adviſeable, ſince other acts forbid
their acceſs to Court, for all the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to quit their
<hi>Country</hi> or their <hi>Religion,</hi> leſt they might hereafter
ſmart for the <hi>Act of Nature,</hi> or the <hi>wickedneſs of any other
Faction,</hi> if not likely, at leaſt not impoſſible. Sacred and profane
ſtory furniſhes us with many inſtances of plots made by <hi>one,</hi> and
father'd on <hi>another party.</hi> And the beaſt in the <hi>Apologue</hi>
with a Lump of Fleſh on his Fore-head, was not imprudent in quitting the
Forreſt upon the Lyons proclamation. <hi>That all horned Beaſts ſhould at
their peril depart;</hi> for when he was asked, <hi>why he ran away,</hi> he
anſwered, <hi>If the Lyon ſaid, the Lump was a Horn, it would be in vain
for him to contend, or after hope an eſcape.</hi> And really, I ſee no
ſecurity in the change of <hi>Religon,</hi> ſince people are ſo impoſed
upon, to ſwallow Gudgeons in believing, if that indeed they do what they ſo
loudly ſpeak, that after all Oaths, Teſts, and Sacraments, they are ſtill
<hi>Papiſts in Maſquerade,</hi> and have <hi>Bulls</hi> and
<hi>Dispenſations</hi> for diſſembling and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; a Suppoſition not
only idiculous, but reflective upon the Wiſdom of the <hi>Parliament:</hi>
for if no mark of diſcrimination, nor ſcent can be found to diſcover the
blown Deer, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from the reſt of the Herd, 'tis in vain to
hunt, and the Parliament have taken great pains to find out papiſts, but to
no purpoſe, a cenſure no leſs ſevere upon them, than 'twould be folly
in the <hi>Pope</hi> to expect Obedience from thoſe he abſolved from all
Obligations: For the Oaths do not only allow them to ſwear Fealty and Homage
to <hi>one Prince,</hi> but bind them to renounce <hi>all others,</hi> and
being ſo taken in the plain literal Sence and Acceptation of the Words, there
can be no reſerve. For however the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are accuſed to allow
<hi>Equivocation</hi> and <hi>mental Reſervation,</hi> they are not yet
arrived to that impudence of owning to the World ſo monſtrous an Impiety.
And therefore I hope the new <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>London</hi> re abuſed
by their Friend who publiſhes their having taken the Oathes and Abjurations
in their <hi>own meanings,</hi> and tell<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153272:10"/>us, that how
contrary ſoever, that may be to the <hi>plain Words,</hi> yet 'tis
conformable to the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Intention of the Impoſers, the
Parliament.</hi> A new Doctrine I confeſs, and very expreſſive of a
tender Conſcience. For if you examine it aright, you will find it turns the
deſign of Oaths, into Folly, leaving them no force, nor Men under any
Obligation. For it is all one <hi>to ſwear,</hi> and <hi>not to ſwear at
all,</hi> if the taker of the Oath may do it in <hi>his own,</hi> and not in
the <hi>Impoſers Senſe;</hi> it reconciles extreams, makes a narrow
half-pynt <hi>City Conſcience,</hi> and one as large and wide as the great
Tun of <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> the ſame. Here will be no longer <hi>stumbling at
straws, nor leaping over Blocks: ſtraining at a Gnat, and ſwallowing a
Camel will be a Jeſt;</hi> all will go down with equal eaſe, and all tyes
between King and Subjects will ceaſe; the Oaths of <hi>Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and
<hi>Allegiance</hi> are Fopperies, Chaff to cath the credulous; neither will be
perjured, if the one prove a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> or the other a <hi>Rebel.</hi> So
monſtrous a Tenet ought not to ſcape pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Animadverſion. And I do as
verily believe, a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> ſham'd that Pamphlet upon the
<hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs,</hi> as that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> made <hi>Venner</hi>'s
<hi>plot,</hi> and the two following of 1662, and 1666. altho in their ſtead
the poor innocent <hi>Fifth Monarchy men</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks</hi> paid the
reckoning at <hi>Tyburn.</hi> But if indeed there were
<hi>Diſpenſations</hi> to he had, is it ſuppoſable by Men (<hi>Fools
may take a Wind-Mill for an inchanted Caſtle, and</hi> Don Quixor-<hi>like,
fight against the wind</hi>) that any would forfet <hi>Liberty, Fortune</hi> or
<hi>Country,</hi> much more <hi>Life it ſelf,</hi> as is notorious many have
done, rather than take theſe Oaths.</p>
            <p>There is then no cauſe to fear the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will be
undiſcoverable, or that they can be terrible, conſidering the ſmallneſs
of their Number, tho the D. of Y. ſhould come to govern. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that
it would not be in his Power, nor for his Intereſt, as is already ſhewn, to
innovate the <hi>Conſtitutions of Church and State,</hi> nothing like it can
be dreaded from his <hi>Character,</hi> which all knowing, and
diſintereſted Perſons will thus give you; <hi>That he is a Prince of ſo
many admirable Endowments and excellent Qualifications both by Nature &amp; by
Art, as make it a queſtion to which of the two he is moſt indebted, and
render him matchleſs in the preſent, and rarely exceeded by any in former
Ages.</hi> He is not only of innate Courage, fearleſs and intrepid as a Lion,
but a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of great Experience, both at Land and Sea; preferring the
laſt more for his Countries ſafety and honour, than his own eaſe or
pleaſure; In all things temperate and ſober, in his Actions between Man and
Man nicely juſt, in his Word and Promiſes ſtrictly faithful, and
reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly punctual, ſincere in his Friendſhips and Profeſſions, a
kind Brother, and a dutiful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, an obliging Husband, and an excellent
Maſter, a great lover of Buſineſs, ſedulous and diligent, and
indefatigable in Labours; affable and eaſy of acceſs, patient in hearing
and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patching the meaneſt, of quick Apprehenſion, and ſound
Judgement; and tho in this traduc'd by Envy, Malice, and Deſign; yet I defy
the worſt of his Enemies, to inſtance wherein he ever ſpake impertinently
on any Subject. He is what the <hi>French</hi> call <hi>un bonest homme,</hi>
too compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive to be <hi>Engliſh'd</hi> by one Word, ſignifying, A
<hi>Perſon compoſed of all the good Qualities that make Men truly
valuable;</hi> He was born to retrieve the ſinking Glory of the <hi>Engliſh
Nation,</hi> a Truth once readily acknowledged by all, and would be ſo at
this day, if the contrary were not impoſed by the cunning of the Ambitious,
under the diſguiſe and pretence of <hi>Zeal for Religion;</hi> in which,
whatever his private Opinions are, he deſires not a liberty he would not
grant. He is not of a narrow perſecuting Spirit, ſo much in love with his
own, as to deſpiſe the Opinions of <hi>all others.</hi> He would have every
Man enjoy the <hi>right of Nature, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> without
diſturbance of the publick peace. In a Word, he is brave and generous,
liberal but not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, reſolute but not ſtubborn, great but not proud,
humble but not abject; in all his Actions he ſhews himſelf a
<hi>Gentleman,</hi> but in none forgets that he is a <hi>Prince.</hi> He is not
an <hi>Angel,</hi> but a <hi>Man,</hi> and therefore not free from ſome
Paſſions and human Fraitlties; but in the World there cannot be found a
Prince with fewer. He needs not boaſt the Statues of his Anceſtors, he has
a ſtock of fame and vertue of his own, large enough to make him great. He is
doubly related to the Title of his Grand Father <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th, by
Birth, and by his Sufferings. Without flattery he may be accounted <hi>the
moſt illuſtrious of modern Hero</hi>'s, and very little, if at all out-done
by <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> or by <hi>Alexander,</hi> by <hi>Hannibal</hi> or by
<hi>Scipio.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh, Scots,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> have been
Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of this Truth to their Honour and Renown. The <hi>French,</hi>
the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Flemmings</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the
<hi>German, Sweed</hi> and <hi>Dane,</hi> have ſeen and felt his Actions to
their coſt &amp; to<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153272:11"/>thir Envy. And what has this great Min
done, to have felt his Vertues and his Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels wither'd and forgot? Is it for
expoſing his perſon, like a common Sea man for the Glory of the
<hi>Engliſh Nation?</hi> or is the change of the peoples Affections owing to
the alteration of his Opinions about <hi>the Modes and Circumſtances of
Religion,</hi> for, in reality 'tis <hi>no more?</hi> Oh! no, it proceeds from
the ſubtilty of ſome Fellow-Subjects, who under pretence of <hi>Love for
the publick, and Zeal for Religion,</hi> deſign for themſelves a
<hi>Tyranny,</hi> and therefore endeavour by all the arts of Malice to remove
out of the way of their Ambition this great Perſon, <hi>the only
Obſtacle;</hi> impoſing upon the World; that all themſelves aim at, are
intended by the D. when nothing is further from his thoughts, than <hi>a
purpoſe of governing</hi> England <hi>otherwiſe than by the eſtabliſh'd
Laws.</hi> A Lye may for a while ſully and eclipſe the brighteſt
Innocence, but at length it muſt break through thoſe Clouds with a greater
increaſe of Luſtre and of Glory. 'Tis good <hi>Machiavilian</hi> policy,
<hi>calumniare fortiter, aliquid adherebit; Throw Dirt enough, ſome of it
will stick.</hi> There was a time, when only <hi>Vice</hi> was ſafe, and
honourable, and nothing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal but to be <hi>brave and vertuous;</hi> and the
<hi>best Citizens</hi> were therefore proſcribed; and why ſhould it be
wondred that in <hi>England,</hi> as well as in <hi>Rome,</hi> or
<hi>Athens,</hi> no <hi>Ariſtides</hi> ſhould be baniſhed for <hi>being
too good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſidering that <hi>Laws may bind a King</hi> (which to
deny is folly and madneſs) and that there are already enough &amp; more may
be added, to prevent a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Succeſſors miſchieving
<hi>Protestant Subjects,</hi> if there were no Laws to this purpoſe, yet
prudence and right reaſon would continue to us the enjoyment of Liberty,
Property and Religion, let never ſo bigotted a <hi>Papiſt</hi> aſcend the
Throne: much leſs is any alteration to be apprehended from the <hi>Duke,</hi>
who beſides all thoſe Obligations, does further ſecure us by his
<hi>innate Goodneſs and temper:</hi> 'tis no wonder his Majeſty ſhould
ſo often forbid the intermedling with <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> ſince he
could not but conclude from ſo unreaſonable a procedure, ſomething elſe
might be deſigned, beſides the <hi>ſecurity of the proteſtant Religion;
under the ſaireſt Tufts of Graſs, we know Snakes are likelieſt to be
hid.</hi> For firſt, there was no cauſe to conclude the D. ſhould
certainly out-live his Royal Brother; or if he did, that he would or could
alter the Government; nor ſecondly, that he ſhould always continue of his
preſent Opinion in Religion, ſince he that <hi>once changed</hi> might
<hi>do ſo again,</hi> upon the alteration of his temper, never at a ſtand,
or the ſame in any perſon, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his fuller conſideration of the
Controverſie. But if in this he ſhould remain unalterable, and chance to
out-live him, his conſenting to ſuch an Act would never prevent great
Effuſion of Bloud, civil War, and unaccountable Miſeries and Calamities;
for let Men Fancie what they pleaſe, the D. would ſtill have no ſmall
party in <hi>England,</hi> all or moſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> and
<hi>Ireland</hi> would be entirely for him; he is accounted by both a Prince of
their Bloud, and by their Laws, who no more than thoſe of <hi>England</hi>
allow their Kings mortal, to be their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign upon the Death of his
predeceſſor, without the Formalities of Proclamation or Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and
who knows not that the united force of theſe two Kingdoms with the power
within the third, would counter ballance all the reſt of the Might of
<hi>England.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> being
diſtinct Kingdoms, and governed by Laws of their own <hi>Parliaments,</hi> no
Act made by that of <hi>England</hi> can be binding in any inſtance, much
leſs in excluding their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign. Now over and above thoſe advantages,
all the popiſh Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> (and they, if united, are too
ſtrong for the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) would be on his ſide, if
<hi>Religion</hi> have that power ſome Men apprehend. But if it have not, yet
<hi>France</hi> would account it their intereſt to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the D. in his
poſſeſſions, for then they two joining (to which nothing elſe could
invite the King of <hi>England</hi>) all rubs in the way of the <hi>Univerſal
Monarchy</hi> would be certainly remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And what would the Conſequence of
this be, but a running into the inconveniency we would now avoid,
<hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> otherwiſe not only an
uncertain, but an imaginary Fear. Though this ſhould not happen in the
perſon of the D. yet his excluſion may otherwiſe occaſion it. For let
it be conſidered, that to keep him out, <hi>an Army muſt be
maintained,</hi> which will encreaſe our <hi>Charge,</hi> another great evil;
and that Army muſt have a <hi>General,</hi> and who can be aſſured that
either the then <hi>King</hi> or the <hi>General,</hi> or <hi>both</hi> ſhall
not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and changing with their
<hi>Religion</hi> their <hi>Tempers,</hi> by the asſiſtance of that Army
ſettle an <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>Deſpotick power,</hi> enſlave us,
and exerciſe an uncontroulable <hi>Tyranny</hi> over our Minds, our Bodies
and Eſtates Remember what our late revolution did produce, and 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153272:11"/>forget not the <hi>Rump</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Oliver,</hi> whoſe publick Taxes
were Mountains compared with thoſe Mole-Hills under which we now ſeem ſo
much to ſuffer and be buried. <hi>If the Rider gives his Horſe the Reins,
he knows not whither an unbridled Fury may at laſt carry him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not imposſible, but the putting by the D. may end in a
depoſing the <hi>preſent poſſeſſor:</hi> For if the late King was
not only reputed <hi>a papist,</hi> but executed for <hi>deſigning the
Introduction of popery,</hi> though all the World knows he was a <hi>ſtiff
aſſerter of,</hi> and <hi>a Martyr for the proteſtant Religion;</hi> and
if now a <hi>preſumed papist</hi> be declared <hi>unfit to ſucceed;</hi>
how much more unfit muſt a <hi>papist</hi> be declared <hi>to Govern?</hi>
And how can we be aſſured, <hi>that Caracter</hi> ſhall not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be
fixt upon <hi>our King,</hi> when we know one of the Brethren was not long
ſince Indicted for ſaying, <hi>The D. was a Papiſt, and the K. little
better?</hi> and that already every Member of the <hi>Church of England,</hi>
the very <hi>Biſhops,</hi> all but <hi>Two</hi> not excepted, are called
<hi>papiſts in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade?</hi> Succeſs makes men bold againſt God and
Man; and we arrive not at the heighth of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence but by degrees, <hi>nemo
repente fit turpiſſimus.</hi> Read the <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> and obſerve
not the <hi>Whispers,</hi> but the <hi>loud Diſcourſes,</hi> and then tell
me whether you can call this <hi>a groundleſs Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi> If the King
cannot pardon the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> or any <hi>Criminal,</hi> (which that
Noble-man no more is, upon the account of his pardon, than all his
predeceſſors who have ſhewn him the way) then indeed he is no longer the
<hi>Supreme,</hi> and may well enough be concluded <hi>already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd</hi>
more than in <hi>Effigie.</hi> And yet this Doctrine is maintain'd by the
<hi>Loyal Conſiderer of the great and wighty Conſiderations touching the
Succeſſion,</hi> and publickly ſold in the <hi>Court of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts;</hi>
and another poſition no leſs pernicious, held by him and many of the ſame
principles, <hi>That there can be Treaſon againſt the State, againſt the
people, againſt the Government,</hi> excluding the <hi>Kings perſon,</hi>
for whoſe ſecurity alone the Satutes have provided againſt
<hi>Treaſons,</hi> not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it agreeable to Reaſon, or our own
Poſitive Laws, to exalt above the <hi>King's,</hi> the <hi>Majeſty of the
People.</hi> If ſuch Doctrines be openly avow'd, witneſs that
<hi>Pamphlet,</hi> and the <hi>Modeſt Anſwerer of the King's Declaration
about his Marriage,</hi> 'tis no wonder the King ſhould depend upon other
Guards for his Safety, than the <hi>Affections of,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>ſuch
loyal Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt had many Promiſes of being
made <hi>great and glorious,</hi> provided he would part with his moſt
faithful Friends and Counſellors, then ſtiled <hi>diſaffected and evil
Miniſters;</hi> and by granting ſome ſuch ſmall Requeſts, he gave
encouragement for <hi>asking,</hi> and left himſelf no room for <hi>denying
greater.</hi> And indeed he was made <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
exalted</hi> from an Earthly to a Heavenly Throne, from a <hi>King</hi> to be a
<hi>Martyr.</hi> Who can be ignorant, that however to demoliſh a ſtrong
Fort, or a Tower well built, it be neceſſary to labour long about <hi>the
Out-works and the Walls with Cannon and with Pick-ax, yet one only puff, though
but weak, of a Princes Folly, or a Private mans Ambition, who has good store of
Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Money, and Wit, is able to make the ſtrongeſt Empire totter and
fall, before the Ruine be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. Athelſtan</hi> the great <hi>Saxon</hi>
King, out of jealouſie of State, was perſwaded to expoſe to the mercy of
the Seas his Brother <hi>Elwyn,</hi> and thereby endanger'd the loſs of his
Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; of which when he was put in mind, by his Cup-bearer's ſaying, upon
recovering with one Foot the ſlip of the other, <hi>See how one Brother helps
another,</hi> he cryed out, <hi>Ah Traytor, liveſt thou to upbraid me of that
Folly, of which your ſelf was the Author?</hi> and thereupon cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to
be immediatly executed. <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth had ſcap'd Depoſition and
Murder, had he not conſented to his Uncle the Good Duke of
<hi>Gloceſter</hi>'s deſtruction, who living kept him ſafe, and dying
threw him down. After the ſame method did the Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi>
bring about the Ruine of the Protector in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time;
perſwading him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move his Brother the <hi>Admiral,</hi> his only Bulwark
and Support; of which Contrivance, though too late, be died not inſenſible,
leaving to Poſterity a Caution to avoid the Rock on which he ſplit. The
extraordinary Careſſes of a reconcil'd Enemy are ever to be diſtruſted,
and always to be accounted dangerous; and he may well apprehend a Deſign,
that finds ſuch, or any man, more than himſelf, ſollicitous for his
Safety. The Wolves pretending kindneſs to the Sheep, offer'd to make a
<hi>League</hi> with them, but not till they firſt had <hi>baniſh'd away
their Dogs;</hi> this they no ſooner did, than they paid with the
forſeiture of their Necks, the price of their <hi>credulity,</hi> and their
<hi>folly.</hi> Nor is the Fathers Legacy to his Sons, of a <hi>Bundle of
Twigs,</hi> leſs inſtructive, theſe which <hi>ſingle</hi> may with
eaſe, cannot with difficulty, <hi>whilst uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153272:12"/>he
bent or broken. <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> is more uſeful for the
Aſpirers to, than the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of a Crown; and he that ſuffers
himſelf to be impos'd upon <hi>in one,</hi> lays himſelf open to <hi>all
Inſtances;</hi> and will quickly perceive, the more he grants, the leſs he
is able to refuſe When a Prince finds his Subjects inſiſt upon things
unreaſonable or unneceſſary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed contrary to his
poſitive Commands, as in the Caſe of <hi>Succesſion,</hi> 'tis time to
look about him, and ſuſpect they intend ſomewhat more than yet they
diſcover.</p>
            <p>The ſureſt way to compaſſe ones purpoſe, is to pretend
the contrary; and if you will be with ſucceſs a Sinner, and
<hi>exquiſitly wicked,</hi> you muſt pretend to be a Saint, and
<hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily devout.</hi> You may with more ſafety eat your
<hi>Cheſtnuts,</hi> if, Monkey-like, you make uſe of the <hi>Cats
Claws</hi> to pull them out of the Fire. You cannot hope to enſlave your
<hi>Country,</hi> but under the ſpecious Names of <hi>Reformation</hi> and
<hi>Liberty.</hi> The people may be gull'd, and drawn to <hi>bite,</hi> if the
<hi>Hook</hi> be baited with a <hi>fitting Fly.</hi> If you will ſet up
<hi>Presbytery,</hi> you muſt pretend at firſt only to run down
<hi>Popery:</hi> when the <hi>Popiſh Lords</hi> are outed, it will be eaſie
after to exclude the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That here has been a long time, and ſtill is a carrying on,
<hi>a deſign to ſubvert the Government and the Religion of the Nation,</hi>
I perfectly agree with the Writer of <hi>The growth of Popery and Arbitrary
Government:</hi> But <hi>I</hi> wiſh the Gentleman had nam'd, as he eaſily
might, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators.</hi> If you will believe, againſt all Truth
and Reaſon, the before mentioned <hi>Anſwerer to the Declaration,</hi> they
are center'd in his R. H. and <hi>He alone has been the Author of the
Miniſters miſcarriages, or the Chances of ill Fortune, that have hapned
ſince the Kings Reſtauration.</hi> One might have though <hi>Popery</hi>
alone had been Crime enough to render him odious, without loading him with the
<hi>Burden of others.</hi> Muſt they make him not onely <hi>preſumptive
Heir,</hi> but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Criminal?</hi> But I confeſſe, he that
ſo much defames, and ſo irreverently treats <hi>the King,</hi> may with
leſſe hazard belie <hi>his Brother.</hi> The end is viſible, That what
<hi>Juſtice</hi> cannot, <hi>popular Fury</hi> and the <hi>Rabble</hi>
ſhould, take away the <hi>Beeing</hi> of that <hi>much injur'd Prince.</hi>
Hence it is, he is ſaid to have been <hi>the Author of the Fire of
London:</hi> His never to be forgotten pains and Diligence to ſuppreſs
thoſe Flames, are ill requited. He was then known to be a <hi>zealous
Proteſtant,</hi> and could he joyn with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who are now
call'd the <hi>Authors,</hi> in a mean ſo deſtructive of <hi>Religion?</hi>
And if that were the Deſign, what hinders its being effected? If the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> muſt be acquitted, ſurely the <hi>Duke</hi> ought, in
that the <hi>Phanatick Plotters</hi> executed in <hi>April</hi> before,
confeſſ'd at <hi>Tyburn</hi> they had ſo contriv'd that <hi>fatal Scene,
that it could not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry:</hi> And indeed the <hi>Event</hi> verified
their <hi>Prediction to aday,</hi> as to the <hi>Fire,</hi> though not to the
reſt of their <hi>intended Tragedie.</hi> When <hi>Nero</hi> ſet
<hi>Rome</hi> on fire, he commanded <hi>Chriſtianos ad Leones;</hi> an ill
Preſident for <hi>Chriſtian Commonwealths: No man can make himſelf
innocent by throwing his Crimes upon others.</hi> But thus it fares with his R.
H. as well in <hi>this</hi> as in <hi>many more Inſtances.</hi> He is ſaid
to be the <hi>Author of the Popiſh Plots,</hi> though not only <hi>Oates</hi>
and <hi>Bedloe</hi> (the laſt confirming it at his Death) have acquitted him,
but likewiſe my Lord <hi>Danby</hi> tells you, in his Printed Caſe, <hi>The
King was ſo far from believing it, that it had never been brought upon the
Stage, but for the D's Importunity.</hi> This alone, if there were not many
more, is a ſufficient Argument of his <hi>Innocence,</hi> and <hi>abhorrence
of the Fact;</hi> and yet now (forſooth) <hi>he muſt have revealed it after
the King had given him the intimation, that the Conſpirators might convey
away their Papers. If</hi> ſo, <hi>I</hi> pray, why were <hi>Colman's,</hi>
or any others found? But it will appear on examination, that
<hi>Beddingfield</hi> no ſooner receiv'd the Packet, (of which how Doctor
<hi>Tongue</hi> could inform the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> then in
<hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> 27 mils beyond <hi>Windſor,</hi> ſo as to be with
the King on that account within few hours after, is a Riddle) than he brought
it to the <hi>Duke,</hi> telling him, <hi>there was miſchief deſign'd to
his R. H. in particular, or to himſelf, or the Papists in general, for that
the incloſed Letters were forged, and one of them from Dr.</hi> Fogorthy,
<hi>to whoſe Perſon as well as Name he was, till then a perfect
Stranger.</hi> This Packet the D. gave to the R. that very day, about the
laſt of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> who looking on one of the Letters, ſaid, <hi>he
had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en the hand before.</hi> Some
eight days after, Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> ſent by <hi>Coleman</hi>
the whole Diſcovery, with which the ſecond time the D. acquainted his
Majeſty, who yet ſpoke not to the D. of the matter. The reſt of that
<hi>Libel</hi> is as falſe as theſe two Particulars, which therefore for
brevity <hi>I</hi> paſſe over, no man in his Wits being able to think it
needs any other<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153272:12"/>Confutation than the Fire. But before
<hi>I</hi> conclude, give me leave to tell you, <hi>That the D. has not
expoſed his Perſon on all occaſions for the honour of the Engliſh
Nation, but whereever he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed carried Victory along with him, which in his
abſence was not found.</hi> In the <hi>firſt war</hi> he <hi>beat the
Dutch,</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> he <hi>got the better;</hi> but in
<hi>both,</hi> the change of <hi>Admirals</hi> alter'd our Succeſs: And
whatever falſe ſteps our Miniſters have made, whoſe Baſtards are not
to be laid at his doors, he is no otherwiſe accountable for them, then you or
<hi>I,</hi> who had no power to reſiſt. Every one knows who have been the
publick and loſe Managers of Affairs; and theſe can witneſs, the D. could
never be reckon'd in their number. He had no hand in <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the
Fleet</hi> in the firſt War, nor in halling it up at <hi>Chatham</hi> before
a Peace concluded. He was not privy to the Advice of <hi>breaking the Triple
League,</hi> nor making an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> which he no ſooner
heard, than he oppoſ'd, foretelling, with <hi>Caſſandra's</hi> Fate, the
Iſſue. He influenc'd not a War with <hi>Holland,</hi> nor ſetting upon
their <hi>Smyrna-Fleet</hi> before a Breach declared. <hi>Delenda eſt
Carthago was not his Sentence,</hi> nor his <hi>Act the Shutting up the
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer?</hi> nor was he the Author of <hi>Injunctions againſt the
Bankers,</hi> nor of <hi>uſurping the Commons Right of filling their own
Vacancies,</hi> nor conſequently, of the other Part or Link of this Chain and
Contrivance, <hi>the Project of Indulgence;</hi> though, to give him his due,
he was for purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſteddily Reſolutions, when once taken; the contrary
would be a leſſning our power, and a making us ridiculous at home and
abroad. Afterwards, when theſe Meaſures were broken, and new ones embraced,
he was for purſuing the <hi>Intereſt of England</hi> in defence of the
<hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> and did as verily believe, and was as much
impos'd upon, as the moſt credulous in <hi>England,</hi> that a War againſt
<hi>France</hi> was then really purpoſed, when deſired by both Houſes, in
1678/7. His preparations to hazard his Perſon in that Expedition, are
notorious Evidences of this Truth. Yet ſuch is his misfortune, that after all
his Endeavours for the good of his Country, he is reputed <hi>a Lover of the
French Intereſt,</hi> though none be more hated by that <hi>Crown,</hi> (an
undenied proof of the mali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the
Imputation) whoſe unwearied dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence has been formerly employ'd, and may
now be well ſuſpected to foment and keep up diviſions between the
<hi>King</hi> and <hi>his Subjects,</hi> the only way to prevent our oppoſing
<hi>his long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned Dominion.</hi> An Obſervation, that alone ought to
invite us to an Union, and a mutual Confidence, and to ſtudy in the Spirit of
Moderation, the healing of our Breaches; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, <hi>That no Reaſon of
State can be uſeful to the Publick, or juſtifie any Actions contrary to the
Laws both of God and Nations;</hi> That it is a ſhame and a reproach upon us
abroad, and an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience at home, to have a <hi>Plot</hi> kept ſo long
on foot, wherein all who ſhould be found guilty upon <hi>unqueſtionable
Evidence,</hi> might have been made <hi>long ſince Exemplary.</hi> A ſpeedy
and impartial proceeding in this Caſe, without <hi>heat</hi> or
<hi>paſſion,</hi> or conſideration of <hi>Parties,</hi> or of
<hi>Intereſt,</hi> will remove all our <hi>Jealouſies and Fears,</hi>
ſettle us upon the immovable Rocks of <hi>Truth and Honour,</hi> and acquit
and vindicate to the World, That an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> is not
influenc'd by men, whoſe <hi>Ambition</hi> leads them to ſtudy their
<hi>own private,</hi> more than the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Good;</hi> That they ſerve
their King and Country for <hi>Glory,</hi> and for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not
for <hi>Gain</hi> or <hi>Preferment;</hi> That they deſign nothing but the
<hi>preſervation of their Rights, Libertis, and Religion,</hi> by the Methods
of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>prudence;</hi> which without doubt may be for ever
ſecured by the Laws already in force, or other new Additions,
notwithſtanding a <hi>Popiſh Soveraign.</hi> The Kings of <hi>England</hi>
have bound, and may again limite their Power with their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in
<hi>Parliament:</hi> But if this Truth be denied, becauſe of that Maxim in
our Laws, <hi>The King can do no wrong;</hi> it cannot, That their Miniſters
and Officers, who muſt be, and are accountable for all, and puniſhable for
Illegal Actions, may be ſo confin'd, as may make our Fears unreaſonable of
any <hi>Encroachments</hi> or <hi>Innovations,</hi> let <hi>never ſo many
Popiſh Princes</hi> much leſſe <hi>any one,</hi> ſucceed. Whoever
ſuggeſts the contrary, is impoſed upon by <hi>Ignorance, Intereſt,</hi>
or the <hi>Malice of crafty and deſigning Achithophels,</hi> who prefer their
<hi>particular Advantage</hi> to <hi>Religion and Liberty,</hi> no other way
really to be endangered, but by debarring the D. his <hi>Right of
Succeſſion;</hi> which once paſt into an <hi>Act,</hi> will, in caſe he
ſurvive, moſt certainly-bring upon the <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> Horrour and
Confuſion, Deſolation and Miſery, and all the ſad Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a
<hi>Civil War.</hi> Evils ſo far from your Temper and Inclination, that I
need not caution<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153272:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>you againſt ſo much madneſſe
and Folly, as inevitably attends the not regarding the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Advice,
<hi>My ſon, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar God, and Honour
the King; and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I have written, I have written in obedience to your
<hi>Commands,</hi> the love of <hi>Truth,</hi> and zeal for the
<hi>Publick,</hi> being (as you know) neither <hi>Courtier</hi> nor
<hi>Penſioner,</hi> never was, or like to be, addicted to <hi>Popery,</hi>
not obliged by <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Duke</hi> in any <hi>particular Grace or
Favor,</hi> but being wholly <hi>Independent,</hi> and having ſomething to
loſe, and ſenſible no others can ſuffer by <hi>War</hi> and
<hi>Rebellion,</hi> I have uſed the ſame freedom without, as I hope you
will within doors, for preventing thoſe Calamities which ſeem to do more
than threaten the Nation; from which, nothing but <hi>Gods Providence,</hi> in
the Wiſdom and Moderation, Courage and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our King and Parliament,
can defend this unhappie and diſtracted Kingdom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
